<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>shares on M5E&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>https://blog.m5e.de/tags/shares/</link>
    <description>Recent content in shares on M5E&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 25 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://blog.m5e.de/tags/shares/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>The Difference between Wirecard and Steinhoff</title>
      <link>https://blog.m5e.de/post/the-difference-between-wirecard-and-steinhoff/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.m5e.de/post/the-difference-between-wirecard-and-steinhoff/</guid>
      <description>Wirecard and Steinhoff are both companies of German origin which had accounting scandals. In this post I want to describe why these two accounting scandals are completely different and why I choose to take a long position in Steinhoff after the scandal, although I did make a profit with a short position in Wirecard.
I am writing this article because I want to describe that shorting a stock with an accounting scandal / fraud isn&amp;rsquo;t always the best option.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;Wirecard and Steinhoff are both companies of German origin which had accounting scandals. In this post I want to describe why these two accounting scandals are completely different and why I choose to take a long position in Steinhoff after the scandal, although I did make a profit with a short position in Wirecard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am writing this article because I want to describe that shorting a stock with an accounting scandal / fraud isn&amp;rsquo;t always the best option. Sometimes this can be a chance for a long position.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;the-wirecard-scandal&#34;&gt;The Wirecard Scandal&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wirecard is a German payment processor and financial services provider. It was higher valued than any German Bank and viewed as very successful by many German Investors because of a growing revenue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2020 it was reported in an audit that €1.9 billion were &amp;ldquo;missing&amp;rdquo;. I shorted Wirecard after the announcement because it meant that the majority of Wirecards revenue didn&amp;rsquo;t exist while there were multiple billion Euro of credit from banks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I realized that there was a way higher debt to the creditors than actual revenue or profit which could pay for the credit, so there was no real way that Wirecard could save itself from insolvency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, Wirecard is a payments provider used by companies — which company does trust a payment provider which manipulates balance sheets?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;the-steinhoff-scandal&#34;&gt;The Steinhoff Scandal&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Steinhoff International is an international retail holding company. Before the scandal it was the second-biggest furniture company in the World after IKEA.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Basically the scandal which took off in 2017 was that Steinhoff manipulated transactions worth of $7.36 billion from the years 2009 to 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now comes one important part: The revenue alone in 2017 was nearly 19 billion Euro!!! Even if you subtract all manipulated transactions from that there is still value!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Steinhoff also is a holding company which holds many different companies which can be sold. That&amp;rsquo;s what happened after the scandal: Many subsidiaries were sold.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;the-difference&#34;&gt;The Difference&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the financial side:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wirecard made up most of the revenue&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Steinhoff didn&amp;rsquo;t made up most, but part of the revenue&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the strategic side:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wirecard was basically one company which hadn&amp;rsquo;t much to sell&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Steinhoff had many companies with actual real estate and products — many things to sell&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;my-opinion&#34;&gt;My Opinion&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I bought Steinhoff shares after the scandal because I estimated that after selling some of the subsidiaries there would be enough money for paying the creditors and restructuring the company.
That process is still ongoing and Steinhoff still exists. Why? Because they simply had more value and the manipulations were in an area where it was possible to pay them down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I shorted Wirecard because there was noting to hope. With basically all revenue made up there is no real revenue which could help paying the credits down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You should look at the actual numbers after an accounting scandal. I also know there were investigations about an accounting issue at GE, but I didn&amp;rsquo;t see it effecting the share price too much — because the numbers in question were too small.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Putting all accounting scandals into the same bucket is wrong, but I experienced that happens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(To be honest I was laughing my ass off because there are German finance influencers which always talked bad about Investors in Steinhoff but then were heavily invested in Wirecard, didn&amp;rsquo;t see that scandal coming and even invested after there were many signs that the balance sheet was faked)&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Analyzing the profitability of gTLD registry operators</title>
      <link>https://blog.m5e.de/post/analyzing-the-profitability-of-gtld-registry-operators/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.m5e.de/post/analyzing-the-profitability-of-gtld-registry-operators/</guid>
      <description>I am a very big DNS nerd and have always registered new domains for my projects before I even made the concept of my new ideas. We had tests about the Domain Name System at my professional school and I can&amp;rsquo;t remember I ever not scored the highest&amp;hellip;
So as someone who currently pays for 33 domains a year of which all are for private projects and none generates money I had an idea for a new gTLD which I wanted to operate.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;I am a very big DNS nerd and have always registered new domains for my projects before I even made the concept of my new ideas.
We had tests about the Domain Name System at my professional school and I can&amp;rsquo;t remember I ever not scored the highest&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So as someone who currently pays for 33 domains a year of which all are for private projects and none generates money I had an idea for a new gTLD which I wanted to operate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;New generic top-level domains have a high entry barrier. It&amp;rsquo;s expensive (plan about 200k USD alone for the valuation from the ICANN) and you also have high recurring costs - but is it profitable to operate such a TLD?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first gTLD application round closed in April 2012 and some of the first applicants were already founded years before that.
Some of these new operators are public traded companies and others have to report their balance sheet to governments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Soooo &amp;hellip;. There is data available about those new operators and before I decide if I wanna put such much money on a new TLD I (from an investor perspective) want to know how profitable new gTLDs are.
(As a side note: I am not so rich to operate a new gTLD alone - I would need some support from other investors too ^^)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s why I am writing this post. I need to validate if an investment in a new gTLD is profitable and if the needed energy pays out.
As a modern investor there are tons of other opportunities which pay dividends, interest and more. So if you invest in something specific you should have a good return and reason for that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;registry-operators&#34;&gt;Registry operators&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;donuts&#34;&gt;Donuts&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Donuts Inc is a private domain name registry with 242 new gTLDs. It is the biggest of the new operators by number of TLD endings. The German Wikipedia page about them was initially written by me on the 15 July of 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately I haven&amp;rsquo;t found much financial info about their profit, so they can&amp;rsquo;t simply evaluated by me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;minds--machines&#34;&gt;Minds + Machines&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They are great for a valuation because Minds + Machines Group Limited is a public traded gTLD operator. They weren&amp;rsquo;t profitable for many years, but they were in 2019.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s look at the numbers for the Total comprehensive income / (loss) for the year:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2013: Loss of 222,029 GBP&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2014: Loss of 3,832,128 GBP&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2015: Loss of 677,936 GBP&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2016: Loss of 2,782,107 GBP&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2017: Loss of 84,584 GBP&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2018: Loss of 8,836,970 GBP&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2019: Income of 932,983 GBP&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Minds + Machines also published a June 2020 Interim Report which shows a profit. So I hope the long loss period is over. The share price has decreased in the years because of the bad financials&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have taken the chance to buy some shares because if they turned to profit, then the company is undervalued based on the current share price in my opinion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;dotberlin&#34;&gt;dotBERLIN&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;dotBERLIN GmbH &amp;amp; Co. KG is the German private operator of &amp;ldquo;.berlin&amp;rdquo;. The fine thing about German companies is that they have to report the balance sheets and you can get old balance sheets from the &amp;ldquo;Bundesanzeiger&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The data is not as fresh as from public traded companies, but this analysis is not about fresh data - it&amp;rsquo;s about statistically profitability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A look at the balance sheet doesn&amp;rsquo;t show us an Income statement, but we can see a &amp;ldquo;Shortfall not covered by equity&amp;rdquo; for the years 2019, 2018, 2017, 2016, 2015, 2014, 2013, 2012, 2011, 2010, 2009&amp;hellip; - at that point I just went directly to 2006 and there was also this shortfall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So to me, it looks like dotBERLIN wasn&amp;rsquo;t profitable since founding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is investing in gTLD a good thing for the world? Not really. New gTLD require new servers which need electricity which could be produced environmentally harmful whereas you could invest your money in e.g. new electricity sources like solar or wind parks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many of these providers operated very long without any profit. However some of them (like Minds + Machines) are profitable now and I am invested in Minds + Machines because they are cheap (in my opinion) on the stock exchange, considering they are now profitable and operate with a lovely business model (subscription based service which is essential if you have an online-business)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But you shouldn&amp;rsquo;t take the decision easy if you wanna start a new gTLD registry. As noted - this kind of business seem to take long until it&amp;rsquo;s profitable and other business models like building a new solar park can be better predictable, faster profitable and are better for the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you start a new gTLD, you should expect many years without profit and the need for fresh money from investors. So - it&amp;rsquo;s a bad idea for the most of us.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Workhorse Group Story</title>
      <link>https://blog.m5e.de/post/the-workhorse-group-story/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.m5e.de/post/the-workhorse-group-story/</guid>
      <description>The Workhorse Group Incorporated is a EV company which primarily produces delivery vans and got lately popular with a rising share price because it was viewed as one of the possible winners of an 8 billion USPS contract to replace old delivery vans.
This contract busted, however I started writing this article before the deal busted - so don&amp;rsquo;t be surprised by the high numbers.
I owned this stock for several years and wanna display my view of the company in this blog post.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;The Workhorse Group Incorporated is a EV company which primarily produces delivery vans and got lately popular with a rising share price because it was viewed as one of the possible winners of an 8 billion USPS contract to replace old delivery vans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This contract busted, however I started writing this article before the deal busted - so don&amp;rsquo;t be surprised by the high numbers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I owned this stock for several years and wanna display my view of the company in this blog post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-usps-deal&#34;&gt;The USPS Deal&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;WKHS has a bad history with the USPS. E.g. a USPS driver was hurt during a prototype test. This isn&amp;rsquo;t the first USPS Deal on which WKHS had bid, more later on&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Competition for WKHS is Oshkosh (with Ford) and Karsan. Oshkosh had also offered a EV solution based on the Ford E-Transit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I thought Oshkosh has a very good chance because they are one of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Top_100_Contractors_of_the_U.S._federal_government&#34;&gt;Top 100 Contractors of the U.S. federal government&lt;/a&gt;. They have lots of experience while Workhorse never had such big contracts and would need help to produce lots of vehicles in a short time (at WKHS they assembled the vehicles via hand in the past, not automated in a factory)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oshkosh won the Deal, however the Valuation of this two stocks before that wasn&amp;rsquo;t on par. WKHS was way higher valuated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-valuation&#34;&gt;The Valuation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Would the Workhorse Group have won an 8 billion contract they probably won&amp;rsquo;t be able to produce all new vehicles in one year. But even if they would do that: Oshkosh had more than 8 billion revenue in 2019 and had a market cap of 6,78 billion USD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Workhorse had at 36,19 USD per stock a market cap of 4,36 billion. So the market cap already was in the area of a company with 8 billion revenue. I don&amp;rsquo;t see any reason why a higher valuation should be justified.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the valuation already had a winning of the contract and a really big EV bonus priced in. It may be fair compared to other EV companies like Tesla, but it definitely isn&amp;rsquo;t fair if you take good old school value figures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-cycle&#34;&gt;The Cycle&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Workhorse Stock is a Story Stock. This is not the first bid for a USPS Deal from Workhorse and you can see when they did bid on a big contract in the stock price history. Most of the times the big deals bust.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Current CEO Duane Hughes has a media background - perfect for marketing a story and if you read a few of the many short reports you see that this is the way with which the management had made money: Market the Story of the big deal and sell shares.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;future&#34;&gt;Future&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dubious YouTube Videos and bad finances should have been a big red flag for every common investor but the EV-Hyped Robinhood Community and Cathie Wood&amp;rsquo;s ARK Invest have pushed this stock without looking too much on the fundamentals and competition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So at the time of the writing the stock crashed after the announcement of the USPS Oshkosh Deal more than 47 percent to 16 USD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can&amp;rsquo;t say for sure if the stock will go up some time in the future again, BUT I am pretty sure if the stock goes up, it will be because some POSSIBLE Deal will get announced again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Make one thing clear: This wasn&amp;rsquo;t a traditional investment, this was a bet on a single Deal which made the most part of the valuation. That&amp;rsquo;s the reason I sold my shares - I don&amp;rsquo;t wanna make bets, I want to own profitable companies which share part of the profit with me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are in the stock market because of Bets, you probably should reconsider your Strategy. Because busted Stories like this can destroy your portfolio.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why Bumble is overvalued</title>
      <link>https://blog.m5e.de/post/why-bumble-is-overvalued/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.m5e.de/post/why-bumble-is-overvalued/</guid>
      <description>Yesterday Bumble had it&amp;rsquo;s initial public offering (IPO). The starting price was 43 USD, a valuation of more than 8 billion and it shot up to 76 USD, a valuation of over 13 billion.
Despite this high valuation, the company lastly made a net loss and only a few hundred million ($376.6 million) in revenue.
The Risk The current market for Tech, EV and Cannabis stocks is in a hype bubble.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;Yesterday Bumble had it&amp;rsquo;s initial public offering (IPO). The starting price was 43 USD, a valuation of more than 8 billion and it shot up to 76 USD, a valuation of over 13 billion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite this high valuation, the company lastly made a net loss and only a few hundred million ($376.6 million) in revenue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-risk&#34;&gt;The Risk&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The current market for Tech, EV and Cannabis stocks is in a hype bubble. I made profit with some overvalued stocks and currently sell these and rebalance my portfolio with more value stocks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But this is not the only risk. I&amp;rsquo;ve used Dating Apps since multiple months (I also made a &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.m5e.de/post/fighting-tinderplusplus-malware/&#34;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt; about a problem with Tinder) and I think the market will evolve:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;enter-the-world-of-facebook&#34;&gt;Enter the World of Facebook&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Facebook launched its own Dating service: Facebook Dating&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think this will dominate the market in a few years - why?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nearly all popular Dating Apps use Facebook Data / Login for registration and validation of the user
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Facebook already has data like Profile Photos, Workplace, Interests,&amp;hellip; which are important in the wold of online dating&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Facebook already has methods to validate profiles&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Facebook already has a bigger user base than all of the dating competition
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To me it seems like the user base of Facebook Dating is already bigger than the user base of Bumble in my local area&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve encountered no limits in swipes or other things
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All features which are premium on the competition Apps are free on Facebook&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve encountered no Ads in Facebook Dating&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I guess this depends on the individual, but I&amp;rsquo;ve got more matches in a few days on Facebook Dating than in multiple months on Bumble&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Facebook promotes social connections - you see who is Friends with other Facebook Friends of you on Facebook
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This adds validation - you trust the other side more that it is not a fake profile&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why should users register with Facebook on Third-Party-Apps if Facebook already provides a superior Dating experience?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Currently many people don&amp;rsquo;t know about Facebook Dating, but Facebook is a Advertising Platform with a giant user base - so it should be very easy to gain more and more people until the competition dies out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It looks like the Investors in Bumble aren&amp;rsquo;t aware that this big competitor is out there and the IPO money was needed for Bumble to have a chance fighting them.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On the 23andMe and VGAC Merger</title>
      <link>https://blog.m5e.de/post/on-the-23andme-and-vgac-merger/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.m5e.de/post/on-the-23andme-and-vgac-merger/</guid>
      <description>On the 4th February 2021 23andMe and VG Acquisition Corp announced that they will merge, bringing 23andMe into the public.
As VGAC is already tradable in the public market, the shares have skyrocketed to 19 USD. But this is crazy&amp;hellip;
Why this is crazy? First you should know that the initiators of a SPAC commonly have additional rights to e.g. buy additional shares. They also mostly pay 10 USD per share.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;On the 4th February 2021 23andMe and VG Acquisition Corp announced that they will merge, bringing 23andMe into the public.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As VGAC is already tradable in the public market, the shares have skyrocketed to 19 USD. But this is crazy&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-this-is-crazy&#34;&gt;Why this is crazy?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First you should know that the initiators of a SPAC commonly have additional rights to e.g. buy additional shares. They also mostly pay 10 USD per share. I don&amp;rsquo;t go more into detail here, but I want to talk about the shareholders which buy VGAC at the current 19 USD price WITHOUT additional rights like the initiators.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you look at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://vgacquisition.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/02/23andMe-Investor-Presentation.pdf&#34;&gt;Investor Presentation&lt;/a&gt; these VGAC shareholders will only get 11 % of the combined company! BUT the market cap of VGAC at 19.05 USD is 876.30 Mn!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So if you buy VGAC at 19 USD you don&amp;rsquo;t get 23andMe at a $3.5 billion valuation like Vigrin and the other investors - Nooo, you buy at a way higher price. 19 USD per VGAC share, 11 % of VGAC go into 23andMe would result into a nearly 8 billion valuation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To put it into comparison: At 19 USD per share you nearly buy at a valuation (8 billion) at which the institutional investors bought Ancestry ($4.7 billion) and 23andMe ($3.5 billion) combined.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also: 23andMe had declining revenue in the past years and does only make around 200 million revenue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You buy a business at a valuation at 8 billion which makes only around 200 million revenue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to buy 23andMe you should wait till the merger is done because the current VGAC market cap is way too high considering existing VGAC shareholders will only get a little part of the combined company.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A alternative investment Idea could be OraSure Technologies Inc - these are the producers of the diagnostic testing kits which are used by 23andMe and Ancestry. Current market cap only 989,83 Mio USD, the sales have declined from 181,74 Mio in 2018 to 154,60 Mio in 2019 but looks like a fair or even cheap valuation to me.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
