<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>shares on M5E&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>https://blog.m5e.de/tags/shares/</link>
    <description>Recent content in shares on M5E&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 24 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://blog.m5e.de/tags/shares/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>The Workhorse Group Story</title>
      <link>https://blog.m5e.de/post/the-workhorse-group-story/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.m5e.de/post/the-workhorse-group-story/</guid>
      <description>The Workhorse Group Incorporated is a EV company which primarily produces delivery vans and got lately popular with a rising share price because it was viewed as one of the possible winners of an 8 billion USPS contract to replace old delivery vans.
This contract busted, however I started writing this article before the deal busted - so don&amp;rsquo;t be surprised by the high numbers.
I owned this stock for several years and wanna display my view of the company in this blog post.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;The Workhorse Group Incorporated is a EV company which primarily produces delivery vans and got lately popular with a rising share price because it was viewed as one of the possible winners of an 8 billion USPS contract to replace old delivery vans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This contract busted, however I started writing this article before the deal busted - so don&amp;rsquo;t be surprised by the high numbers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I owned this stock for several years and wanna display my view of the company in this blog post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-usps-deal&#34;&gt;The USPS Deal&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;WKHS has a bad history with the USPS. E.g. a USPS driver was hurt during a prototype test. This isn&amp;rsquo;t the first USPS Deal on which WKHS had bid, more later on&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Competition for WKHS is Oshkosh (with Ford) and Karsan. Oshkosh had also offered a EV solution based on the Ford E-Transit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I thought Oshkosh has a very good chance because they are one of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Top_100_Contractors_of_the_U.S._federal_government&#34;&gt;Top 100 Contractors of the U.S. federal government&lt;/a&gt;. They have lots of experience while Workhorse never had such big contracts and would need help to produce lots of vehicles in a short time (at WKHS they assembled the vehicles via hand in the past, not automated in a factory)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oshkosh won the Deal, however the Valuation of this two stocks before that wasn&amp;rsquo;t on par. WKHS was way higher valuated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-valuation&#34;&gt;The Valuation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Would the Workhorse Group have won an 8 billion contract they probably won&amp;rsquo;t be able to produce all new vehicles in one year. But even if they would do that: Oshkosh had more than 8 billion revenue in 2019 and had a market cap of 6,78 billion USD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Workhorse had at 36,19 USD per stock a market cap of 4,36 billion. So the market cap already was in the area of a company with 8 billion revenue. I don&amp;rsquo;t see any reason why a higher valuation should be justified.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the valuation already had a winning of the contract and a really big EV bonus priced in. It may be fair compared to other EV companies like Tesla, but it definitely isn&amp;rsquo;t fair if you take good old school value figures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-cycle&#34;&gt;The Cycle&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Workhorse Stock is a Story Stock. This is not the first bid for a USPS Deal from Workhorse and you can see when they did bid on a big contract in the stock price history. Most of the times the big deals bust.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Current CEO Duane Hughes has a media background - perfect for marketing a story and if you read a few of the many short reports you see that this is the way with which the management had made money: Market the Story of the big deal and sell shares.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;future&#34;&gt;Future&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dubious YouTube Videos and bad finances should have been a big red flag for every common investor but the EV-Hyped Robinhood Community and Cathie Wood&amp;rsquo;s ARK Invest have pushed this stock without looking too much on the fundamentals and competition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So at the time of the writing the stock crashed after the announcement of the USPS Oshkosh Deal more than 47 percent to 16 USD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can&amp;rsquo;t say for sure if the stock will go up some time in the future again, BUT I am pretty sure if the stock goes up, it will be because some POSSIBLE Deal will get announced again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Make one thing clear: This wasn&amp;rsquo;t a traditional investment, this was a bet on a single Deal which made the most part of the valuation. That&amp;rsquo;s the reason I sold my shares - I don&amp;rsquo;t wanna make bets, I want to own profitable companies which share part of the profit with me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are in the stock market because of Bets, you probably should reconsider your Strategy. Because busted Stories like this can destroy your portfolio.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why Bumble is overvalued</title>
      <link>https://blog.m5e.de/post/why-bumble-is-overvalued/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.m5e.de/post/why-bumble-is-overvalued/</guid>
      <description>Yesterday Bumble had it&amp;rsquo;s initial public offering (IPO). The starting price was 43 USD, a valuation of more than 8 billion and it shot up to 76 USD, a valuation of over 13 billion.
Despite this high valuation, the company lastly made a net loss and only a few hundred million ($376.6 million) in revenue.
The Risk The current market for Tech, EV and Cannabis stocks is in a hype bubble.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;Yesterday Bumble had it&amp;rsquo;s initial public offering (IPO). The starting price was 43 USD, a valuation of more than 8 billion and it shot up to 76 USD, a valuation of over 13 billion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite this high valuation, the company lastly made a net loss and only a few hundred million ($376.6 million) in revenue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-risk&#34;&gt;The Risk&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The current market for Tech, EV and Cannabis stocks is in a hype bubble. I made profit with some overvalued stocks and currently sell these and rebalance my portfolio with more value stocks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But this is not the only risk. I&amp;rsquo;ve used Dating Apps since multiple months (I also made a &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.m5e.de/post/fighting-tinderplusplus-malware/&#34;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt; about a problem with Tinder) and I think the market will evolve:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;enter-the-world-of-facebook&#34;&gt;Enter the World of Facebook&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Facebook launched its own Dating service: Facebook Dating&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think this will dominate the market in a few years - why?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nearly all popular Dating Apps use Facebook Data / Login for registration and validation of the user
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Facebook already has data like Profile Photos, Workplace, Interests,&amp;hellip; which are important in the wold of online dating&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Facebook already has methods to validate profiles&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Facebook already has a bigger user base than all of the dating competition
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To me it seems like the user base of Facebook Dating is already bigger than the user base of Bumble in my local area&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve encountered no limits in swipes or other things
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All features which are premium on the competition Apps are free on Facebook&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve encountered no Ads in Facebook Dating&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I guess this depends on the individual, but I&amp;rsquo;ve got more matches in a few days on Facebook Dating than in multiple months on Bumble&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Facebook promotes social connections - you see who is Friends with other Facebook Friends of you on Facebook
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This adds validation - you trust the other side more that it is not a fake profile&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why should users register with Facebook on Third-Party-Apps if Facebook already provides a superior Dating experience?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Currently many people don&amp;rsquo;t know about Facebook Dating, but Facebook is a Advertising Platform with a giant user base - so it should be very easy to gain more and more people until the competition dies out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It looks like the Investors in Bumble aren&amp;rsquo;t aware that this big competitor is out there and the IPO money was needed for Bumble to have a chance fighting them.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On the 23andMe and VGAC Merger</title>
      <link>https://blog.m5e.de/post/on-the-23andme-and-vgac-merger/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.m5e.de/post/on-the-23andme-and-vgac-merger/</guid>
      <description>On the 4th February 2021 23andMe and VG Acquisition Corp announced that they will merge, bringing 23andMe into the public.
As VGAC is already tradable in the public market, the shares have skyrocketed to 19 USD. But this is crazy&amp;hellip;
Why this is crazy? First you should know that the initiators of a SPAC commonly have additional rights to e.g. buy additional shares. They also mostly pay 10 USD per share.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;On the 4th February 2021 23andMe and VG Acquisition Corp announced that they will merge, bringing 23andMe into the public.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As VGAC is already tradable in the public market, the shares have skyrocketed to 19 USD. But this is crazy&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-this-is-crazy&#34;&gt;Why this is crazy?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First you should know that the initiators of a SPAC commonly have additional rights to e.g. buy additional shares. They also mostly pay 10 USD per share. I don&amp;rsquo;t go more into detail here, but I want to talk about the shareholders which buy VGAC at the current 19 USD price WITHOUT additional rights like the initiators.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you look at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://vgacquisition.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/02/23andMe-Investor-Presentation.pdf&#34;&gt;Investor Presentation&lt;/a&gt; these VGAC shareholders will only get 11 % of the combined company! BUT the market cap of VGAC at 19.05 USD is 876.30 Mn!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So if you buy VGAC at 19 USD you don&amp;rsquo;t get 23andMe at a $3.5 billion valuation like Vigrin and the other investors - Nooo, you buy at a way higher price. 19 USD per VGAC share, 11 % of VGAC go into 23andMe would result into a nearly 8 billion valuation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To put it into comparison: At 19 USD per share you nearly buy at a valuation (8 billion) at which the institutional investors bought Ancestry ($4.7 billion) and 23andMe ($3.5 billion) combined.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also: 23andMe had declining revenue in the past years and does only make around 200 million revenue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You buy a business at a valuation at 8 billion which makes only around 200 million revenue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to buy 23andMe you should wait till the merger is done because the current VGAC market cap is way too high considering existing VGAC shareholders will only get a little part of the combined company.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A alternative investment Idea could be OraSure Technologies Inc - these are the producers of the diagnostic testing kits which are used by 23andMe and Ancestry. Current market cap only 989,83 Mio USD, the sales have declined from 181,74 Mio in 2018 to 154,60 Mio in 2019 but looks like a fair or even cheap valuation to me.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>