<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>bumble on M5E&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>https://blog.m5e.de/tags/bumble/</link>
    <description>Recent content in bumble on M5E&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 12 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://blog.m5e.de/tags/bumble/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Why Bumble is overvalued</title>
      <link>https://blog.m5e.de/post/why-bumble-is-overvalued/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.m5e.de/post/why-bumble-is-overvalued/</guid>
      <description>Yesterday Bumble had it&amp;rsquo;s initial public offering (IPO). The starting price was 43 USD, a valuation of more than 8 billion and it shot up to 76 USD, a valuation of over 13 billion.
Despite this high valuation, the company lastly made a net loss and only a few hundred million ($376.6 million) in revenue.
The Risk The current market for Tech, EV and Cannabis stocks is in a hype bubble.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;Yesterday Bumble had it&amp;rsquo;s initial public offering (IPO). The starting price was 43 USD, a valuation of more than 8 billion and it shot up to 76 USD, a valuation of over 13 billion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite this high valuation, the company lastly made a net loss and only a few hundred million ($376.6 million) in revenue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-risk&#34;&gt;The Risk&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The current market for Tech, EV and Cannabis stocks is in a hype bubble. I made profit with some overvalued stocks and currently sell these and rebalance my portfolio with more value stocks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But this is not the only risk. I&amp;rsquo;ve used Dating Apps since multiple months (I also made a &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.m5e.de/post/fighting-tinderplusplus-malware/&#34;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt; about a problem with Tinder) and I think the market will evolve:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;enter-the-world-of-facebook&#34;&gt;Enter the World of Facebook&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Facebook launched its own Dating service: Facebook Dating&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think this will dominate the market in a few years - why?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nearly all popular Dating Apps use Facebook Data / Login for registration and validation of the user
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Facebook already has data like Profile Photos, Workplace, Interests,&amp;hellip; which are important in the wold of online dating&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Facebook already has methods to validate profiles&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Facebook already has a bigger user base than all of the dating competition
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To me it seems like the user base of Facebook Dating is already bigger than the user base of Bumble in my local area&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve encountered no limits in swipes or other things
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All features which are premium on the competition Apps are free on Facebook&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve encountered no Ads in Facebook Dating&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I guess this depends on the individual, but I&amp;rsquo;ve got more matches in a few days on Facebook Dating than in multiple months on Bumble&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Facebook promotes social connections - you see who is Friends with other Facebook Friends of you on Facebook
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This adds validation - you trust the other side more that it is not a fake profile&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why should users register with Facebook on Third-Party-Apps if Facebook already provides a superior Dating experience?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Currently many people don&amp;rsquo;t know about Facebook Dating, but Facebook is a Advertising Platform with a giant user base - so it should be very easy to gain more and more people until the competition dies out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It looks like the Investors in Bumble aren&amp;rsquo;t aware that this big competitor is out there and the IPO money was needed for Bumble to have a chance fighting them.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>