<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.4.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://blog.m5e.de/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://blog.m5e.de/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2018-11-26T22:28:53+01:00</updated><id>http://blog.m5e.de/feed.xml</id><title type="html">M5E’s Blog</title><subtitle>Christoph Miksche's blog about personal and development topics.
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Gitea Auto Update Script</title><link href="http://blog.m5e.de/gitea/update/upgrade/bash/script/2018/11/26/gitea-auto-update-script.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Gitea Auto Update Script" /><published>2018-11-26T21:24:00+01:00</published><updated>2018-11-26T21:24:00+01:00</updated><id>http://blog.m5e.de/gitea/update/upgrade/bash/script/2018/11/26/gitea-auto-update-script</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://blog.m5e.de/gitea/update/upgrade/bash/script/2018/11/26/gitea-auto-update-script.html">&lt;p&gt;I’m a gitea user for a long time now. Gitea is a nice application to build your own light and fast version of git hosting services like GitHub or GitLab.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gitea has one problem thought. It doesn’t update automatically. A issue for that is open nearly 2 years: &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/go-gitea/gitea/issues/518#issuecomment-441742904&quot;&gt;https://github.com/go-gitea/gitea/issues/518#issuecomment-441742904&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If there is one thing that i really hate, it is that a security sensible web application doesn’t update automatically. Because of that i have begun to write a update script for gitea before 4 months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That script has updated my gitea instance multiple times now and as i can see, that many users have the same problem (a german blog post from me is my most visited article from outside germany), i want to show you my solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;warning&quot;&gt;Warning&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As i mentioned - i am no fan of manual upgrades - because of that i write many auto update scripts for my own systems. This scripts often haven’t been tested on other systems and may contain ugly code. 
I am open for the creation of issues or pull requests which optimise my code. You should definitely check the code out and make sure to review it before using it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some creators - e.g. the person behind kanboard - have a strong option against auto updates. There are good reasons for that too - you may not want to crash your application because of a faulty upgrade. I recommend auto updates only if you create auto backups, too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-script&quot;&gt;The Script&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m developing the script on a private gitea instance - but i don’t wan’t to publish the repository there because i forked from a other private repositiory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of that i have published the actual version to github: &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/CMiksche/gitea-auto-update&quot;&gt;https://github.com/CMiksche/gitea-auto-update&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The script was made for a Debian System - i haven’t tested it on other systems but you will definitely encounter errors if you wan’t to use it on Windows, MacOS or a Linux System without systemd (i make bash calls to restart the gitea service).
You may need to modify the script to work on your system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the gitea upgrade changes the template files the automatic update may will destroy your custom design because it is a really simple script and doesn’t check that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-to-use-it&quot;&gt;How to use it&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The usage of my script is easy (please read the paragraphs over this first - it won’t work without modifying it if you have no gitea service or no systemd):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Clone my script on the system:&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;git clone https://github.com/CMiksche/gitea-auto-update.git&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Install requests:&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;sudo pip install requests&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Change the variables in the settings.py file&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Enter the command &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;python updater.py&lt;/code&gt; in your commandline to test the first upgrade&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you want to schedule your updates, edit your &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;/etc/crontab&lt;/code&gt; file and add a call the the script&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s it. Please write a issue if my script doesn’t works. I am caring if people want to use my script ;-)&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I’m a gitea user for a long time now. Gitea is a nice application to build your own light and fast version of git hosting services like GitHub or GitLab. Gitea has one problem thought. It doesn’t update automatically. A issue for that is open nearly 2 years: https://github.com/go-gitea/gitea/issues/518#issuecomment-441742904 If there is one thing that i really hate, it is that a security sensible web application doesn’t update automatically. Because of that i have begun to write a update script for gitea before 4 months. That script has updated my gitea instance multiple times now and as i can see, that many users have the same problem (a german blog post from me is my most visited article from outside germany), i want to show you my solution. Warning As i mentioned - i am no fan of manual upgrades - because of that i write many auto update scripts for my own systems. This scripts often haven’t been tested on other systems and may contain ugly code. I am open for the creation of issues or pull requests which optimise my code. You should definitely check the code out and make sure to review it before using it. Some creators - e.g. the person behind kanboard - have a strong option against auto updates. There are good reasons for that too - you may not want to crash your application because of a faulty upgrade. I recommend auto updates only if you create auto backups, too. The Script I’m developing the script on a private gitea instance - but i don’t wan’t to publish the repository there because i forked from a other private repositiory. Because of that i have published the actual version to github: https://github.com/CMiksche/gitea-auto-update The script was made for a Debian System - i haven’t tested it on other systems but you will definitely encounter errors if you wan’t to use it on Windows, MacOS or a Linux System without systemd (i make bash calls to restart the gitea service). You may need to modify the script to work on your system. If the gitea upgrade changes the template files the automatic update may will destroy your custom design because it is a really simple script and doesn’t check that. How to use it The usage of my script is easy (please read the paragraphs over this first - it won’t work without modifying it if you have no gitea service or no systemd): Clone my script on the system: git clone https://github.com/CMiksche/gitea-auto-update.git Install requests: sudo pip install requests Change the variables in the settings.py file Enter the command python updater.py in your commandline to test the first upgrade If you want to schedule your updates, edit your /etc/crontab file and add a call the the script That’s it. Please write a issue if my script doesn’t works. I am caring if people want to use my script ;-)</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">FreeBSD: nvidia-driver installation</title><link href="http://blog.m5e.de/freebsd/nvidia-driver/installation/2017/11/19/freebsd-nvidia-driver-installation.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="FreeBSD: nvidia-driver installation" /><published>2017-11-19T15:59:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-11-19T15:59:00+01:00</updated><id>http://blog.m5e.de/freebsd/nvidia-driver/installation/2017/11/19/freebsd-nvidia-driver-installation</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://blog.m5e.de/freebsd/nvidia-driver/installation/2017/11/19/freebsd-nvidia-driver-installation.html">&lt;p&gt;After installing FreeBSD to my workstation, i wanted a desktop environment. I’ve installed gnome3 after reading the official documentation &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.freebsd.org/doc/handbook/x11-wm.html&quot;&gt;https://www.freebsd.org/doc/handbook/x11-wm.html&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But nothing has worked. So, i installed the nvidia-driver for my two GPUs. The first documentation i’ve found is from “7.3-RELEASE”: &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.freebsd.org/doc/7.3-RELEASE/usr/share/doc/en/articles/compiz-fusion/nvidia-setup.html&quot;&gt;https://docs.freebsd.org/doc/7.3-RELEASE/usr/share/doc/en/articles/compiz-fusion/nvidia-setup.html&lt;/a&gt;. (I use 11.1-RELEASE)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t use that documentation to make your settings in &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;/boot/loader.conf&lt;/code&gt;! There stands:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;nvidia_load=&quot;YES&quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s simply not right for the newest driver!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should enter the following line:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;nvidia-modeset_load=&quot;YES&quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After that and using nvidia-xconfig to create the Xorg-Config file, my system works now.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">After installing FreeBSD to my workstation, i wanted a desktop environment. I’ve installed gnome3 after reading the official documentation https://www.freebsd.org/doc/handbook/x11-wm.html.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">FreeBSD and Windows 10 Dual-Boot</title><link href="http://blog.m5e.de/freebsd/windows10/dual-boot/2017/11/19/freebsd-windows10-dual-boot.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="FreeBSD and Windows 10 Dual-Boot" /><published>2017-11-19T15:45:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-11-19T15:45:00+01:00</updated><id>http://blog.m5e.de/freebsd/windows10/dual-boot/2017/11/19/freebsd-windows10-dual-boot</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://blog.m5e.de/freebsd/windows10/dual-boot/2017/11/19/freebsd-windows10-dual-boot.html">&lt;p&gt;Yesterday i have installed FreeBSD alongside to a existing Windows 10 instance on my Workstation. Today, i want to show you how to do it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;prerequisites&quot;&gt;Prerequisites&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My setup is a SSD with Windows 10 already installed and more than 100 GB free space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;procedure&quot;&gt;Procedure&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Install FreeBSD normally (but pay attention to use the free space for freebsd during the partitioning).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the install, you can switch to the shell to take final settings. There you can enter the following command:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;boot0cfg -B ada0
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s it. Reboot and everything should work fine ;-)&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Yesterday i have installed FreeBSD alongside to a existing Windows 10 instance on my Workstation. Today, i want to show you how to do it.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">APU2C4 - LED blinks 5 times …</title><link href="http://blog.m5e.de/apu2c4/blink/led/2017/11/16/apu2c4-blinks-5-times.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="APU2C4 - LED blinks 5 times ..." /><published>2017-11-16T16:03:23+01:00</published><updated>2017-11-16T16:03:23+01:00</updated><id>http://blog.m5e.de/apu2c4/blink/led/2017/11/16/apu2c4-blinks-5-times</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://blog.m5e.de/apu2c4/blink/led/2017/11/16/apu2c4-blinks-5-times.html">&lt;p&gt;I bought a APU2C4 Board (from the swiss company “PC Engines GmbH”) and multiple components because i want to build a custom pfSense router.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve ordered the device several weeks ago and haven’t used it until now. That’s because i made a few mistakes (which i want to write now):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;first&quot;&gt;First&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mistake: I used a power supply with 12V and 2A from china.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Visible by: The LED on the back of the device blinks 5 times - then no more again.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Solution: Use a 12V and 3A power supply.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;second&quot;&gt;Second:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mistake: I used a serial cable with Prolific PL2303 Chip and another serial cable with a Gender Changer.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Visible by: I couldn’t connect to the device.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Solution: Don’t use PL2303 Chips and Gender Changer! The following Chips are supported: FTDI / FT232RL and Silicon Labs CP2104&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the way: The support of pc-engines is really fast - great customer experience …&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My new serial cable with FT232RL chip hasn’t arrived yet. I will write more about that device when i encounter new errors …&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I bought a APU2C4 Board (from the swiss company “PC Engines GmbH”) and multiple components because i want to build a custom pfSense router.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">First try of Jekyll</title><link href="http://blog.m5e.de/jekyll/first/post/2017/02/14/first-try-of-jekyll.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="First try of Jekyll" /><published>2017-02-14T20:03:23+01:00</published><updated>2017-02-14T20:03:23+01:00</updated><id>http://blog.m5e.de/jekyll/first/post/2017/02/14/first-try-of-jekyll</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://blog.m5e.de/jekyll/first/post/2017/02/14/first-try-of-jekyll.html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve already using different blog systems like WordPress and Ghost, but this is my try to start a blog in english about personal and development topics with Jekyll.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe is the domain not my best choice (.de is the domain for germany), but as i haven’t any project on it, i will use it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will be using GitHub as hosting service. That will have a few great side effects: you can download my whole blog via git clone, in the same way you could mirror my blog and if you want to notified when a new change happens, you could subscribe my Blog via the “Watch” Function of GitHub.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t like limits. Because of that, i will only push the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;_site&lt;/code&gt; directory to my GitHub Repo. (In that way i can use custom plugins in Jekyll)&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I’ve already using different blog systems like WordPress and Ghost, but this is my try to start a blog in english about personal and development topics with Jekyll.</summary></entry></feed>