<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>M5E&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>https://blog.m5e.de/</link>
    <description>Recent content on M5E&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 24 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://blog.m5e.de/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>The Workhorse Group Story</title>
      <link>https://blog.m5e.de/post/the-workhorse-group-story/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.m5e.de/post/the-workhorse-group-story/</guid>
      <description>The Workhorse Group Incorporated is a EV company which primarily produces delivery vans and got lately popular with a rising share price because it was viewed as one of the possible winners of an 8 billion USPS contract to replace old delivery vans.
This contract busted, however I started writing this article before the deal busted - so don&amp;rsquo;t be surprised by the high numbers.
I owned this stock for several years and wanna display my view of the company in this blog post.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why Bumble is overvalued</title>
      <link>https://blog.m5e.de/post/why-bumble-is-overvalued/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.m5e.de/post/why-bumble-is-overvalued/</guid>
      <description>Yesterday Bumble had it&amp;rsquo;s initial public offering (IPO). The starting price was 43 USD, a valuation of more than 8 billion and it shot up to 76 USD, a valuation of over 13 billion.
Despite this high valuation, the company lastly made a net loss and only a few hundred million ($376.6 million) in revenue.
The Risk The current market for Tech, EV and Cannabis stocks is in a hype bubble.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On the 23andMe and VGAC Merger</title>
      <link>https://blog.m5e.de/post/on-the-23andme-and-vgac-merger/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.m5e.de/post/on-the-23andme-and-vgac-merger/</guid>
      <description>On the 4th February 2021 23andMe and VG Acquisition Corp announced that they will merge, bringing 23andMe into the public.
As VGAC is already tradable in the public market, the shares have skyrocketed to 19 USD. But this is crazy&amp;hellip;
Why this is crazy? First you should know that the initiators of a SPAC commonly have additional rights to e.g. buy additional shares. They also mostly pay 10 USD per share.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Apple environmental friendly?</title>
      <link>https://blog.m5e.de/post/apple-environmental-friendly/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.m5e.de/post/apple-environmental-friendly/</guid>
      <description>Why Apple Products aren&amp;rsquo;t as environmentally problematic as many believe. Apple bashing is popular these days. Louis Rossmann, Hugh Jeffreys and others are talking about repair issues on YouTube, Mark Zuckerberg sees Apple as an unfair competitor and Xiaomi mocks Apple for Not Including Charger and then does the same.
So in this world where Apple bashing is popular I wanna tell you my opinion.
I bought my first new Apple Products this year (primarily caused by the impressive performance of the M1), but I already have used used Apple Devices for a longer period.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Comparison of Email Hosting Possibilities</title>
      <link>https://blog.m5e.de/post/comparison-of-email-hosting-possibilities/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.m5e.de/post/comparison-of-email-hosting-possibilities/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve hosted my own Mailserver in various configurations since more than 6 years now. Since then I&amp;rsquo;ve taken multiple breaks from hosting it myself and explored other solutions for hosting emails with your own domain names.
Because my own Mailserver has lately problems (downtimes) I wanna explore other possibilities of hosting my email addresses.
So let&amp;rsquo;s take a look&amp;hellip;
Self-hosting (VPS, Tools like Mailcow, Mailu, etc) You simply setup a Mailserver with software like Mailcow, Mailu or Mail-in-a-Box on a virtual Server and manage it yourself.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fighting the Tinder&#43;&#43; Malware</title>
      <link>https://blog.m5e.de/post/fighting-tinderplusplus-malware/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.m5e.de/post/fighting-tinderplusplus-malware/</guid>
      <description>People who search for love are more vulnerable than happy couples. Especially people wo lost their Tinder Account because Tinder has banned them.
There is a malware out there which targets exactly this kind of people. If you search for &amp;ldquo;unban tinder&amp;rdquo; on Google and or YouTube you find many videos and sites which recommend the &amp;ldquo;Tinder++&amp;rdquo; App.
Tinder++ aims to bring you free Tinder Gold and unban your Account. People on sites and videos which recommend the App talk that the Tinder ban is only per Device and they found a way to get around this ban.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Benchmarking Go, Crystal, Python and JavaScript</title>
      <link>https://blog.m5e.de/post/benchmarking-go-crystal-python-and-js/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.m5e.de/post/benchmarking-go-crystal-python-and-js/</guid>
      <description>Benford&amp;rsquo;s Law After watching a Netflix documentary about Benford&amp;rsquo;s Law (&amp;ldquo;connected&amp;rdquo; Season 1 Episode 4 &amp;ldquo;Digits&amp;rdquo;), I got really interested in it because it can help detect fraud in e.g. balance sheets. So I searched my favorite programming languages and detected that there is no npm Package for checking Benford&amp;rsquo;s Law.
Sooo &amp;hellip; Long story short: I created nearly identical libraries for doing a Benford&amp;rsquo;s Law check in JavaScript, Go and Crystal.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Switching to Hugo</title>
      <link>https://blog.m5e.de/post/switching-to-hugo/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.m5e.de/post/switching-to-hugo/</guid>
      <description>Moving to Hugo I started this blog as my first blog using a static website generator. Back then I used what everyone else was using: Jekyll.
But Jekyll has it problems. I don&amp;rsquo;t use Ruby for anything else and the management of the dependencies / ruby versions / etc of my static blog was too much for me.
I blog way more often in german on my other WordPress sites and one of the main reasons is that it is easier and Jekyll wasn&amp;rsquo;t as easy as I expected.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Forget Bash, take Python!</title>
      <link>https://blog.m5e.de/bash/script/python/linux/2020/05/22/forget-bash-take-python.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.m5e.de/bash/script/python/linux/2020/05/22/forget-bash-take-python.html</guid>
      <description>I wrote bash scripts for several years now. You can find old bash scripts of mine on GitHub but most of them aren&amp;rsquo;t maintained anymore - and I have a reason for that.
But before I give you my reasons for not using many bash scripts anymore, lets look at the benefits of bash:
 It super easy and you basically already can it if you write Linux / BSD commands There are frameworks out now which give you advanced features like testing It works out of the box on nearly every Linux / BSD system  Okay - sounds good - so whats my problem?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Gitea Auto Update Script</title>
      <link>https://blog.m5e.de/gitea/update/upgrade/bash/script/2018/11/26/gitea-auto-update-script.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Nov 2018 21:24:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.m5e.de/gitea/update/upgrade/bash/script/2018/11/26/gitea-auto-update-script.html</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;m a gitea user for a long time now. Gitea is a nice application to build your own light and fast version of git hosting services like GitHub or GitLab.
Gitea has one problem thought. It doesn&amp;rsquo;t update automatically. A issue for that is open nearly 2 years: https://github.com/go-gitea/gitea/issues/518#issuecomment-441742904
If there is one thing that I really hate, it is that a security sensible web application doesn&amp;rsquo;t update automatically. Because of that I have begun to write a update script for gitea before 4 months.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>FreeBSD: nvidia-driver installation</title>
      <link>https://blog.m5e.de/freebsd/nvidia-driver/installation/2017/11/19/freebsd-nvidia-driver-installation.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 Nov 2017 15:59:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.m5e.de/freebsd/nvidia-driver/installation/2017/11/19/freebsd-nvidia-driver-installation.html</guid>
      <description>After installing FreeBSD to my workstation, I wanted a desktop environment. I&amp;rsquo;ve installed gnome3 after reading the official documentation https://www.freebsd.org/doc/handbook/x11-wm.html.
But nothing has worked. So, I installed the nvidia-driver for my two GPUs. The first documentation I&amp;rsquo;ve found is from &amp;ldquo;7.3-RELEASE&amp;rdquo;: https://docs.freebsd.org/doc/7.3-RELEASE/usr/share/doc/en/articles/compiz-fusion/nvidia-setup.html. (I use 11.1-RELEASE)
Don&amp;rsquo;t use that documentation to make your settings in /boot/loader.conf! There stands:
nvidia_load=&amp;quot;YES&amp;quot; And that&amp;rsquo;s simply not right for the newest driver!
You should enter the following line:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>FreeBSD and Windows 10 Dual-Boot</title>
      <link>https://blog.m5e.de/freebsd/windows10/dual-boot/2017/11/19/freebsd-windows10-dual-boot.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 Nov 2017 15:45:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.m5e.de/freebsd/windows10/dual-boot/2017/11/19/freebsd-windows10-dual-boot.html</guid>
      <description>Yesterday I have installed FreeBSD alongside to a existing Windows 10 instance on my Workstation. Today, I want to show you how to do it.
Prerequisites My setup is a SSD with Windows 10 already installed and more than 100 GB free space.
Procedure Install FreeBSD normally (but pay attention to use the free space for freebsd during the partitioning).
After the install, you can switch to the shell to take final settings.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>APU2C4 - LED blinks 5 times ...</title>
      <link>https://blog.m5e.de/apu2c4/blink/led/2017/11/16/apu2c4-blinks-5-times.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Nov 2017 16:03:23 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.m5e.de/apu2c4/blink/led/2017/11/16/apu2c4-blinks-5-times.html</guid>
      <description>I bought a APU2C4 Board (from the swiss company &amp;ldquo;PC Engines GmbH&amp;rdquo;) and multiple components because I want to build a custom pfSense router.
I&amp;rsquo;ve ordered the device several weeks ago and haven&amp;rsquo;t used it until now. That&amp;rsquo;s because I made a few mistakes (which i want to write now):
First  Mistake: I used a power supply with 12V and 2A from china. Visible by: The LED on the back of the device blinks 5 times - then no more again.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>First try of Jekyll</title>
      <link>https://blog.m5e.de/jekyll/first/post/2017/02/14/first-try-of-jekyll.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Feb 2017 20:03:23 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.m5e.de/jekyll/first/post/2017/02/14/first-try-of-jekyll.html</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve already using different blog systems like WordPress and Ghost, but this is my try to start a blog in english about personal and development topics with Jekyll.
Maybe is the domain not my best choice (.de is the domain for germany), but as I haven&amp;rsquo;t any project on it, I will use it.
I will be using GitHub as hosting service. That will have a few great side effects: you can download my whole blog via git clone, in the same way you could mirror my blog and if you want to notified when a new change happens, you could subscribe my Blog via the &amp;ldquo;Watch&amp;rdquo; Function of GitHub.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Contact &amp; Imprint</title>
      <link>https://blog.m5e.de/contact/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.m5e.de/contact/</guid>
      <description>This is Christoph Daniel Miksche&amp;rsquo;s blog in english. He also offers a german blog at http://christoph.miksche.org.
Legal Disclosure Information in accordance with section 5 TMG
Christoph Miksche
Forststraße 2
97500 Ebelsbach
Contact Telephone: 0176 82532907
E-Mail: christoph[at]miksche[dot]org
Disclaimer Accountability for content The contents of our pages have been created with the utmost care. However, we cannot guarantee the contents&#39; accuracy, completeness or topicality. According to statutory provisions, we are furthermore responsible for our own content on these web pages.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
