<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>M5E&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>https://blog.m5e.de/</link>
    <description>Recent content on M5E&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 22 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://blog.m5e.de/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>The Social Bot Lie</title>
      <link>https://blog.m5e.de/post/the-social-bot-lie/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.m5e.de/post/the-social-bot-lie/</guid>
      <description>Recently this talk was given on the rC3 2021 Chaos Communication Congress:
  In summary, Florian Gallwitz explained that there are no &amp;ldquo;Social Bots&amp;rdquo; which are often covered in newspapers and magazines.
Newspapers and Journalists create stories about AIs which post about political discussions but in reality these &amp;ldquo;Social Bots&amp;rdquo; are just accounts from human beings which write a lot of social media posts, classified as bots.
The real existing &amp;ldquo;bots&amp;rdquo; are dumb systems which e.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;Recently this talk was given on the rC3 2021 Chaos Communication Congress:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/Qwiss4qWuTs&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In summary, Florian Gallwitz explained that there are no &amp;ldquo;Social Bots&amp;rdquo; which are often covered in newspapers and magazines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Newspapers and Journalists create stories about AIs which post about political discussions but in reality these &amp;ldquo;Social Bots&amp;rdquo; are just accounts from human beings which write a lot of social media posts, classified as bots.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The real existing &amp;ldquo;bots&amp;rdquo; are dumb systems which e.g. post blog posts on Twitter (I use systems like that for publishing my content across different social media channels) and you feel if you write with a human being or not, because chatbots aren&amp;rsquo;t that evolved yet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There seem to exist ppl who post propaganda, but these are people, not bots!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This makes complete sense - if you think about it:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If an AI would be that much evolved, wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be the inventor of this the richest human being on earth? The biggest companies like Google, Microsoft and Apple are trying to automate as much as possible for years and invent tools like GitHub Copilot so that writing Code can be partially done by AIs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For creating an AI which seems to react like a human in different situations, you would need a ton of training, very much computing power and lots of people who train the AI every day. It would cost a ton of money, more than you could imagine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why would you use that for political propaganda in one country if you could basically rule the world? Companies would pay you tons of money because such a system could replace so many people, thus make the company more efficient and more money.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s important to note that newspapers use automated systems for writing news about the stock market or the weather since years, however between writing a simple text and replying to users is a big difference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many people unfortunately just read headlines and don&amp;rsquo;t think about it - this is just one of many great talks given on the rC3 2021, there was also a great talk about fairy tales which the west tells itself about Asia (like the Chinese social credit system): &lt;a href=&#34;https://media.ccc.de/v/rc3-2021-xhain-354-painting-tech-dystopi&#34;&gt;https://media.ccc.de/v/rc3-2021-xhain-354-painting-tech-dystopi&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Create fast new posts for your Hugo Blog</title>
      <link>https://blog.m5e.de/post/create-fast-new-posts-for-your-hugo-blog/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.m5e.de/post/create-fast-new-posts-for-your-hugo-blog/</guid>
      <description>Static site generators like Hugo, Jekyll or Nuxt are awesome. They provide way faster delivery of your contents to your customers than any PHP solution like WordPress.
Unfortunately you have to create the Markdown files for your content yourself, but because every single post has a filename, title, date and often tags as well as a status for draft, I created a simple tool which takes care of doing exactly that.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;Static site generators like Hugo, Jekyll or Nuxt are awesome. They provide way faster delivery of your contents to your customers than any PHP solution like WordPress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately you have to create the Markdown files for your content yourself, but because every single post has a filename, title, date and often tags as well as a status for draft, I created a simple tool which takes care of doing exactly that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just enter &lt;code&gt;np The Title of your blog post&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;np&lt;/code&gt; will create a file inside the content/post directory with your Title, date, draft status (default: true) and tags which are simply the words in your title.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://asciinema.org/a/455172&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://asciinema.org/a/455172.svg&#34; alt=&#34;asciicast&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can find the project on GitLab: &lt;a href=&#34;https://gitlab.com/cmiksche/np&#34;&gt;https://gitlab.com/cmiksche/np&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Problem with Finance APIs</title>
      <link>https://blog.m5e.de/post/the-problem-with-finance-apis/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.m5e.de/post/the-problem-with-finance-apis/</guid>
      <description>Since 2014 I invest and trade with stocks. Since then, I always wanted to create programs which make my life as an Investor easier and since then my journey with always reliving finance API problems started.
Unfortunately I didn&amp;rsquo;t find my first PHP scripts which tried to get stock data - so I don&amp;rsquo;t remember which API stopped back then, but the rest of my journey was well documented with the help of Git.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;Since 2014 I invest and trade with stocks. Since then, I always wanted to create programs which make my life as an Investor easier and since then my journey with always reliving finance API problems started.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately I didn&amp;rsquo;t find my first PHP scripts which tried to get stock data - so I don&amp;rsquo;t remember which API stopped back then, but the rest of my journey was well documented with the help of Git.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;yahoo-stock-data-api&#34;&gt;Yahoo Stock Data API&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;# Read Symbols from Database&lt;/span&gt;
symbols &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; datab&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;getSymbols()

&lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;# Get Price Data for each Symbol from yahoo&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; sym &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; symbols:

    url &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;http://finance.yahoo.com/d/quotes.csv?s=&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;sym&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;&amp;amp;f=sabd&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;with&lt;/span&gt; closing(requests&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;get(url, stream&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;True&lt;/span&gt;)) &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;as&lt;/span&gt; r:
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Guess what: The API is not available anymore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;yahoo-currency-data-api&#34;&gt;Yahoo Currency Data API&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;with&lt;/span&gt; urllib&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;request&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;urlopen(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;http://finance.yahoo.com/webservice/v1/symbols/allcurrencies/quote?format=json&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;) &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;as&lt;/span&gt; url:
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Current Currency rates on a stable API? Not with Yahoo!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;coinmarketcap-free-crypto-api&#34;&gt;CoinMarketCap Free Crypto API&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;# Get Market Data&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;with&lt;/span&gt; urllib&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;request&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;urlopen(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;https://api.coinmarketcap.com/v1/ticker/?convert=EUR&amp;amp;limit=0&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;) &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;as&lt;/span&gt; url:
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Free Crypto prices? No! The guys behind CoinMarketCap found out that offering a free and open service is stupid and now ask for money!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;finsymbols-python-lib&#34;&gt;Finsymbols Python lib&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mainly get obtained via web scraping. I didn&amp;rsquo;t check all the functions, but it seems that many are outdated now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;iex-exchange&#34;&gt;IEX Exchange&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back in the day I was crazy about this. A whole exchange which advertised it was made for developers with a free API.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;iexurl &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;https://api.iextrading.com/1.0/stock/&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;sym&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;/quote&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;with&lt;/span&gt; urllib&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;request&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;urlopen(iexurl) &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;as&lt;/span&gt; url:
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ha! Markets move too fast to provide the same URL for a longer period! You now have to use a new one, and it is not even free anymore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;exchangeratesapiio&#34;&gt;exchangeratesapi.io&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Was a free and open source service with API for current exchange rates from the ECB.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The guy behind it sold it to a company which is owned by a big American Corporation. Of course, they now ask for money, even while there are many APIs which offer the same for free.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;learnings&#34;&gt;Learnings&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are not even all APIs that changed - I used other ones before that. I use finance APIs since 2014, and I never encountered one which didn&amp;rsquo;t change after a few years or months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So to rely on any finance API alone sounds stupid to me now because even the biggest players in this area changed their API dramatically multiple times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-solution&#34;&gt;The Solution&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think the only solution for that problem is to create a wrapper around multiple APIs, check which APIs are online and give the fastest responses and deliver the information from these APIs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because there are many APIs which deliver the data from the European Central Bank and have a similar / compatible API to what exchangeratesapi.io had back in the day, I created two wrappers for currencies:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/CMiksche/exchangerates-wrapper&#34;&gt;exchangerates-wrapper&lt;/a&gt; outputs a URL to an API which is online, and you can also define which currencies need to be supported from the API. It&amp;rsquo;s written in TypeScript and usable for projects in the Node ecosystem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://gitlab.com/cmiksche/go-currency-wrapper&#34;&gt;go-currency-wrapper&lt;/a&gt; is the same, but for projects which use the Go programming language.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-about-stocks-and-crypto&#34;&gt;What about stocks and crypto?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I plan similar projects for stocks and cryptocurrencies, I am currently not sure if or when I will release it to the public. However, other projects also have similar ideas: &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/piquette/finance-go/issues/14&#34;&gt;https://github.com/piquette/finance-go/issues/14&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Evergrande situation</title>
      <link>https://blog.m5e.de/post/the-evergrande-situation/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.m5e.de/post/the-evergrande-situation/</guid>
      <description>Over the last days Evergrande China, the 2nd largest property developer in China after revenue, was in all financial news. More than 1.5 million homes are planned by Evergrande and it has $300 billion in liabilities.
There are fears that Evergrande China will cause another financial crisis like in 2008, comparable to the Lehman Brothers insolvency. I am watching this very carefully. Most of my personal Assets are stocks and a big decline in the stock market could mean damage comparable of loosing multiple yearly incomes to me.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;Over the last days Evergrande China, the 2nd largest property developer in China after revenue, was in all financial news. More than 1.5 million homes are planned by Evergrande and it has $300 billion in liabilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are fears that Evergrande China will cause another financial crisis like in 2008, comparable to the Lehman Brothers insolvency. I am watching this very carefully. Most of my personal Assets are stocks and a big decline in the stock market could mean damage comparable of loosing multiple yearly incomes to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-problem&#34;&gt;The Problem&lt;/h2&gt;

  &lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34; data-dnt=&#34;true&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Seems like that &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/Evergrande?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#Evergrande&lt;/a&gt; problem already affects the financial markets…&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Christoph Miksche (@CMiksche) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/CMiksche/status/1439953316340015104?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;September 20, 2021&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If they company fails to pay the liabilities it could cause a systematic insolvency because the banks wouldn&amp;rsquo;t the get money and the market would be flooded with very cheap homes which could cause insolvency of other property developers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem would affect China first because western banks don&amp;rsquo;t have a big share in the 300 billion - mostly Chinese banks gave the money but if there would be a systematic failure in China the rest of the world would feel that too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most countries have strong trade relationships with China - e.g. the German Car industry sells most of the Cars in China.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s not only real damage, fears of that situation already caused a decline in nearly every stock market index.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-solution-opinion-of-experts&#34;&gt;The Solution (Opinion of Experts)&lt;/h2&gt;

  &lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34; data-dnt=&#34;true&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;As far as I understand it most experts believe the chinese government will support the competition to takeover parts of Evergrande and solve the problem that way without a crisis.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;If that doesn&amp;#39;t happen we could have a Lehman moment.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Christoph Miksche (@CMiksche) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/CMiksche/status/1440249711051427844?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;September 21, 2021&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most Experts think this will be solved like Long-Term Capital Management. To make it short: in the LTCM case, the competition took over parts of the business and the government supported it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-thoughts&#34;&gt;My Thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;

  &lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34; data-dnt=&#34;true&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Over the last months the chinese goverment destroed whole sectors (e.g. E-Learning) without any help - so I wouldn&amp;#39;t bet on support.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Also the company already tried to sell parts without much success and the competiton already has high debts...&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Christoph Miksche (@CMiksche) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/CMiksche/status/1440249732756959241?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;September 21, 2021&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The solution which the Experts share has two assumptions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The government is interested to help solving the issue.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The competition can take over parts from Evergrande&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have very high doubts that this assumptions are correct.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;About 1: In the last months, China created rules which destroyed whole sectors. E.g. they destroyed the whole E-Learning sector. It is basically forbidden to sell E-Learning services. So it doesn&amp;rsquo;t look like the top priority of the government would be supporting financial markets or companies. It looks more like it is more important to them that the government is stronger than companies. Letting financial markets fail could cause a big financial trouble but it actually could be in the favor of the politicians who want a strong government and weak companies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Western &amp;ldquo;Experts&amp;rdquo; make the assumptions China would act like a capitalist nation, but China isn&amp;rsquo;t the US. So we can&amp;rsquo;t expect they make the same decisions as we would make. They have different interests and priorities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;About 2: The competition has also debts. I am not sure if they are strong enough to take over such a big transaction. Remember: more than 1.5 million homes and 300 billion liabilities.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How I write my Journal</title>
      <link>https://blog.m5e.de/post/how-i-write-my-journal/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.m5e.de/post/how-i-write-my-journal/</guid>
      <description>Recently I came across a blog post which described some Tips how to write a Journal on Hacker News.
This interested me because I also write a Journal since multiple years (since the 20th March of 2018 to be precise and if we don&amp;rsquo;t count my Journals I had as a child) and it already helped me in multiple occasions.
The author of the article asked himself multiple questions every day and because I think that is too much pressure I want to describe how I do it.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;Recently I came &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=28530120&#34;&gt;across&lt;/a&gt; a blog post which described some Tips how to write a Journal on Hacker News.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This interested me because I also write a Journal since multiple years (since the 20th March of 2018 to be precise and if we don&amp;rsquo;t count my Journals I had as a child) and it already helped me in multiple occasions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The author of the article asked himself multiple questions every day and because I think that is too much pressure I want to describe how I do it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-it-can-be-helpful&#34;&gt;Why it can be helpful&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some possible use cases:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Search when you bought an Item and find out if it still has warranty&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Find out which stock you bought at which price&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When was the trip with your girlfriend again?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How did your business grew so successful?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What did you do back on &amp;hellip;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To summarize: If you keep track of your daily life you can look up everything even if you don&amp;rsquo;t remember something anymore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-i-write-it&#34;&gt;How I write it&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wanted something simple which will last till I die.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a software developer, I use tools like Git for versioning files and Markdown for writing documents (this blog post itself is also written as a Markdown document). Additionally to that, I already had a wiki which was realized as a bunch of Markdown documents and folders in a Git repository hosted on a Raspberry Pi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I used my existing wiki, added a new folder &amp;ldquo;Journal&amp;rdquo; and inside that a folder for the year. That directory contained files named after each month - &amp;ldquo;03.md&amp;rdquo; for example - which had a title for every day and bullet points for every thought.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This simple system exists till this day with a small change that I moved it from my Raspberry Pi to my self-hosted Gitea instance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-personal-finance-is-connected-with-that&#34;&gt;Why personal finance is connected with that&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since this year I use &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/beancount/beancount/&#34;&gt;beancount&lt;/a&gt; to track all my finances in a very similar approach: Files have a special syntax with lines for every transaction and that files get tracked in a Git repository.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks to the parsable syntax you can create reports of your finances (like income and expenses) thus have a better overview of where your money flows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because I trade with stocks since 2014 my journal was heavily used for tracking stock transactions which helped me a lot but obviously such a bookkeeping computer language is a way better solution for that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine you bought a stock but because your Depot was moved to another broker, you don&amp;rsquo;t see the value anymore at which you bought. Now you would have to search old documents of that transaction to find out at which price you can sell to make a profit. In some similar cases this personal tracking of my finances helped me a lot and I would recommend every stock trader writing down the transactions with a system like beancount.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Difference between Wirecard and Steinhoff</title>
      <link>https://blog.m5e.de/post/the-difference-between-wirecard-and-steinhoff/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.m5e.de/post/the-difference-between-wirecard-and-steinhoff/</guid>
      <description>Wirecard and Steinhoff are both companies of German origin which had accounting scandals. In this post I want to describe why these two accounting scandals are completely different and why I choose to take a long position in Steinhoff after the scandal, although I did make a profit with a short position in Wirecard.
I am writing this article because I want to describe that shorting a stock with an accounting scandal / fraud isn&amp;rsquo;t always the best option.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;Wirecard and Steinhoff are both companies of German origin which had accounting scandals. In this post I want to describe why these two accounting scandals are completely different and why I choose to take a long position in Steinhoff after the scandal, although I did make a profit with a short position in Wirecard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am writing this article because I want to describe that shorting a stock with an accounting scandal / fraud isn&amp;rsquo;t always the best option. Sometimes this can be a chance for a long position.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;the-wirecard-scandal&#34;&gt;The Wirecard Scandal&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wirecard is a German payment processor and financial services provider. It was higher valued than any German Bank and viewed as very successful by many German Investors because of a growing revenue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2020 it was reported in an audit that €1.9 billion were &amp;ldquo;missing&amp;rdquo;. I shorted Wirecard after the announcement because it meant that the majority of Wirecards revenue didn&amp;rsquo;t exist while there were multiple billion Euro of credit from banks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I realized that there was a way higher debt to the creditors than actual revenue or profit which could pay for the credit, so there was no real way that Wirecard could save itself from insolvency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, Wirecard is a payments provider used by companies — which company does trust a payment provider which manipulates balance sheets?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;the-steinhoff-scandal&#34;&gt;The Steinhoff Scandal&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Steinhoff International is an international retail holding company. Before the scandal it was the second-biggest furniture company in the World after IKEA.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Basically the scandal which took off in 2017 was that Steinhoff manipulated transactions worth of $7.36 billion from the years 2009 to 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now comes one important part: The revenue alone in 2017 was nearly 19 billion Euro!!! Even if you subtract all manipulated transactions from that there is still value!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Steinhoff also is a holding company which holds many different companies which can be sold. That&amp;rsquo;s what happened after the scandal: Many subsidiaries were sold.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;the-difference&#34;&gt;The Difference&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the financial side:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wirecard made up most of the revenue&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Steinhoff didn&amp;rsquo;t made up most, but part of the revenue&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the strategic side:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wirecard was basically one company which hadn&amp;rsquo;t much to sell&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Steinhoff had many companies with actual real estate and products — many things to sell&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;my-opinion&#34;&gt;My Opinion&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I bought Steinhoff shares after the scandal because I estimated that after selling some of the subsidiaries there would be enough money for paying the creditors and restructuring the company.
That process is still ongoing and Steinhoff still exists. Why? Because they simply had more value and the manipulations were in an area where it was possible to pay them down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I shorted Wirecard because there was noting to hope. With basically all revenue made up there is no real revenue which could help paying the credits down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You should look at the actual numbers after an accounting scandal. I also know there were investigations about an accounting issue at GE, but I didn&amp;rsquo;t see it effecting the share price too much — because the numbers in question were too small.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Putting all accounting scandals into the same bucket is wrong, but I experienced that happens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(To be honest I was laughing my ass off because there are German finance influencers which always talked bad about Investors in Steinhoff but then were heavily invested in Wirecard, didn&amp;rsquo;t see that scandal coming and even invested after there were many signs that the balance sheet was faked)&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Delete and Resync a Crypto-Wallet on your server</title>
      <link>https://blog.m5e.de/post/delete-and-resync-a-crypto-wallet-on-your-server/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.m5e.de/post/delete-and-resync-a-crypto-wallet-on-your-server/</guid>
      <description>I stake a Cryptocurrency based of Peercoin on a Server since years. Multiple months ago this stopped because of the following error:
Coind: kernel.cpp:372: unsigned int GetStakeModifierChecksum(const CBlockIndex*): Assertion `pindex-&amp;gt;pprev || pindex-&amp;gt;GetBlockHash() == (!fTestNet ? hashGenesisBlock : hashGenesisBlockTestNet)&#39; failed.  This Error often comes when your Blockchain is corrupted. The cause of my problem was an unexpected downtime.
To fix this:
 Stop the Daemon Backup the Folder of the Coin Delete everything except wallet.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;I stake a Cryptocurrency based of Peercoin on a Server since years. Multiple months ago this stopped because of the following error:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Coind: kernel.cpp:372: unsigned int GetStakeModifierChecksum(const CBlockIndex*): Assertion `pindex-&amp;gt;pprev || pindex-&amp;gt;GetBlockHash() == (!fTestNet ? hashGenesisBlock : hashGenesisBlockTestNet)&#39; failed.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This Error often comes when your Blockchain is corrupted. The cause of my problem was an unexpected downtime.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To fix this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stop the Daemon&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Backup the Folder of the Coin&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Delete everything except wallet.dat, peers.dat and *.conf&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Start the Daemon again (&lt;code&gt;/path/to/coin/src/Coind -daemon -datadir=/path/to/coin/folder/&lt;/code&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also published a German blog post about &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.wronnay.net/altcoins-vom-source-code-kompilieren/&#34;&gt;compiling AltCoins&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Problem with Odoo</title>
      <link>https://blog.m5e.de/post/the-problem-with-odoo/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.m5e.de/post/the-problem-with-odoo/</guid>
      <description>The history with Odoo started with TinyERP / OpenERP which was a free ERP System. This was a great idea and pioneered the open source ERP environment.
But in the last years the name and the vision changed. Now Odoo provides besides the ERP part also a CRM, CMS, Blogs, Forums, E-commerce (Online-Shops), Timesheet, Project Management, Inventory Management, Recruitment, Spreadsheet, Documents, Email Marketing&amp;hellip;
So in short: Odoo changed from a focus on ERP to an all-in-one solution which seems to cover nearly every application a business needs.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;The history with Odoo started with TinyERP / OpenERP which was a free ERP System. This was a great idea and pioneered the open source ERP environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But in the last years the name and the vision changed. Now Odoo provides besides the ERP part also a CRM, CMS, Blogs, Forums, E-commerce (Online-Shops), Timesheet, Project Management, Inventory Management, Recruitment, Spreadsheet, Documents, Email Marketing&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So in short: Odoo changed from a focus on ERP to an all-in-one solution which seems to cover nearly every application a business needs. And the bad part is Odoo got money from investors for this stupid idea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;i-had-the-same-idea&#34;&gt;I had the same idea&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before I call this idea bullshit I wanna note that I developed an application with the exact same Idea in the past. I didn&amp;rsquo;t finish my work, but basically I started with an CMS in PHP and had the idea to extend it to ERP and various other applications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One reason I stopped working on my idea was because I found out that Odoo was ahead of me (when I started my project, Odoo was still called OpenERP, so I wasn&amp;rsquo;t aware that Odoo just had begun to realize my dream)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the other reason I stopped was because I changed my mind. I worked as a software developer with many ERP, CRM and other business applications back then and created custom software which was connected to this type of software systems. So I had experience with this type of programs and common problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-problem-odoo-wants-to-solve&#34;&gt;The problem Odoo wants to solve&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the problem Odoo and I wanted to solve is the same: Offer one solution for different kind of business software - because traditionally e.g. ERP Systems had no APIs - so as a software developer you had to hack your way to connect e.g. the e-commerce shop with the ERP systems.
This often meant you read or write data directly to the database of the ERP system because the ERP system has no API.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And even if the systems offered an API: This still meant that you have to create a custom piece of software to connect the different systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An all-in-one solution means the data is in the same system - no more costly manual connection making and if you use the UI, then it&amp;rsquo;s also faster to switch to the other business program - e.g. switch from ERP System to Online-Store.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On paper this sounds great: only maintenance one program, only train the employees in one system. Many benefits&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;its-not-so-hard-anymore&#34;&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s not so hard anymore&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today more and more ERP Systems and other kind of business applications offer an API. So the connecting part is cleaner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is software like data mapping tools which make it possible to connect different APIs without any coding experience, additionally to that we live in a world where open source (free) software from all over the world is available and we have software stores which offer plugins and more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So if you have a common type of connection (maybe something like connecting SAP and Magento or WooCommerce), then there is a high chance that out of the shelf software can solve it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-reason-this-is-the-wrong-way&#34;&gt;The reason this is the wrong way&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The all-in-one solution means that Odoo can&amp;rsquo;t focus on one type of application. They need to split up into different teams for different types of applications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes - Odoo has grown and got investor money, so they have many employees and many open source developers BUT they aren&amp;rsquo;t offering only a free ERP System anymore. Even this focus on one part of the business software world was hard and most businesses today don&amp;rsquo;t know Odoo - so they weren&amp;rsquo;t that successful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Players like SAP, Intuit and Infor dominate the ERP market. This was the old competitor landscape. Through the new applications, Odoo now competes additionally to that to Microsoft, Salesforce, Amazon, Magento, Atlassian, MailChimp,&amp;hellip; Basically now the whole business software industry is the competition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do you really think that Odoo can beat the whole software business industry? I don&amp;rsquo;t think so - especially because I already found and fixed a bug in the German version of the Online-Store Module. It&amp;rsquo;s simply not possible for one company to offer the best product for different parts of business software.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a reason that Salesforce is so big in CRM and SAP so big in ERP - there is also a reason why you use a dedicated Online-Store software which is made by another company than your ERP System. Different companies are good in their own specialties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With this broad range of software, Odoo loses focus and that means losing quality. The bigger the range of products, the more worse is the quality and the more impossible it will be for Odoo to offer the best software in each category.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is true in the whole business world - it&amp;rsquo;s the reason we have different companies, but somehow Odoo has still found its way to exist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-new-approach&#34;&gt;My new approach&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As said, I had the same idea. But currently I have only ideas for some types of business software. I don&amp;rsquo;t wanna create an All-In-One solution because I know it would take forever to even offer a bad experience in all types of business software and big companies already excel in some parts of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many IT companies around the world simply exist because they are needed to connect this different kinds of business applications and most of them create custom solutions every time.
I think it would make more sense to offer out of the shelf solutions for connecting these systems and some companies already make this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An Open Source ERP System still would be my choice for a business, but I would prefer something like Tryton - Tryton has a focus on the ERP part and a modular software architecture with a great API.
So this would be perfect for connecting other applications to it. (As a sidenote: Tryton was forked out of an Odoo predecessor)&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Analyzing the profitability of gTLD registry operators</title>
      <link>https://blog.m5e.de/post/analyzing-the-profitability-of-gtld-registry-operators/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.m5e.de/post/analyzing-the-profitability-of-gtld-registry-operators/</guid>
      <description>I am a very big DNS nerd and have always registered new domains for my projects before I even made the concept of my new ideas. We had tests about the Domain Name System at my professional school and I can&amp;rsquo;t remember I ever not scored the highest&amp;hellip;
So as someone who currently pays for 33 domains a year of which all are for private projects and none generates money I had an idea for a new gTLD which I wanted to operate.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;I am a very big DNS nerd and have always registered new domains for my projects before I even made the concept of my new ideas. 
We had tests about the Domain Name System at my professional school and I can&amp;rsquo;t remember I ever not scored the highest&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So as someone who currently pays for 33 domains a year of which all are for private projects and none generates money I had an idea for a new gTLD which I wanted to operate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;New generic top-level domains have a high entry barrier. It&amp;rsquo;s expensive (plan about 200k USD alone for the valuation from the ICANN) and you also have high recurring costs - but is it profitable to operate such a TLD?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first gTLD application round closed in April 2012 and some of the first applicants were already founded years before that. 
Some of these new operators are public traded companies and others have to report their balance sheet to governments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Soooo &amp;hellip;. There is data available about those new operators and before I decide if I wanna put such much money on a new TLD I (from an investor perspective) want to know how profitable new gTLDs are. 
(As a side note: I am not so rich to operate a new gTLD alone - I would need some support from other investors too ^^)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s why I am writing this post. I need to validate if an investment in a new gTLD is profitable and if the needed energy pays out. 
As a modern investor there are tons of other opportunities which pay dividends, interest and more. So if you invest in something specific you should have a good return and reason for that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;registry-operators&#34;&gt;Registry operators&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;donuts&#34;&gt;Donuts&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Donuts Inc is a private domain name registry with 242 new gTLDs. It is the biggest of the new operators by number of TLD endings. The German Wikipedia page about them was initially written by me on the 15 July of 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately I haven&amp;rsquo;t found much financial info about their profit, so they can&amp;rsquo;t simply evaluated by me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;minds--machines&#34;&gt;Minds + Machines&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They are great for a valuation because Minds + Machines Group Limited is a public traded gTLD operator. They weren&amp;rsquo;t profitable for many years, but they were in 2019.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s look at the numbers for the Total comprehensive income / (loss) for the year:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2013: Loss of 222,029 GBP&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2014: Loss of 3,832,128 GBP&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2015: Loss of 677,936 GBP&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2016: Loss of 2,782,107 GBP&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2017: Loss of 84,584 GBP&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2018: Loss of 8,836,970 GBP&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2019: Income of 932,983 GBP&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Minds + Machines also published a June 2020 Interim Report which shows a profit. So I hope the long loss period is over. The share price has decreased in the years because of the bad financials&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have taken the chance to buy some shares because if they turned to profit, then the company is undervalued based on the current share price in my opinion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;dotberlin&#34;&gt;dotBERLIN&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;dotBERLIN GmbH &amp;amp; Co. KG is the German private operator of &amp;ldquo;.berlin&amp;rdquo;. The fine thing about German companies is that they have to report the balance sheets and you can get old balance sheets from the &amp;ldquo;Bundesanzeiger&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The data is not as fresh as from public traded companies, but this analysis is not about fresh data - it&amp;rsquo;s about statistically profitability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A look at the balance sheet doesn&amp;rsquo;t show us an Income statement, but we can see a &amp;ldquo;Shortfall not covered by equity&amp;rdquo; for the years 2019, 2018, 2017, 2016, 2015, 2014, 2013, 2012, 2011, 2010, 2009&amp;hellip; - at that point I just went directly to 2006 and there was also this shortfall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So to me, it looks like dotBERLIN wasn&amp;rsquo;t profitable since founding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is investing in gTLD a good thing for the world? Not really. New gTLD require new servers which need electricity which could be produced environmentally harmful whereas you could invest your money in e.g. new electricity sources like solar or wind parks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many of these providers operated very long without any profit. However some of them (like Minds + Machines) are profitable now and I am invested in Minds + Machines because they are cheap (in my opinion) on the stock exchange, considering they are now profitable and operate with a lovely business model (subscription based service which is essential if you have an online-business)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But you shouldn&amp;rsquo;t take the decision easy if you wanna start a new gTLD registry. As noted - this kind of business seem to take long until it&amp;rsquo;s profitable and other business models like building a new solar park can be better predictable, faster profitable and are better for the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you start a new gTLD, you should expect many years without profit and the need for fresh money from investors. So - it&amp;rsquo;s a bad idea for the most of us.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Workhorse Group Story</title>
      <link>https://blog.m5e.de/post/the-workhorse-group-story/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.m5e.de/post/the-workhorse-group-story/</guid>
      <description>The Workhorse Group Incorporated is a EV company which primarily produces delivery vans and got lately popular with a rising share price because it was viewed as one of the possible winners of an 8 billion USPS contract to replace old delivery vans.
This contract busted, however I started writing this article before the deal busted - so don&amp;rsquo;t be surprised by the high numbers.
I owned this stock for several years and wanna display my view of the company in this blog post.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;The Workhorse Group Incorporated is a EV company which primarily produces delivery vans and got lately popular with a rising share price because it was viewed as one of the possible winners of an 8 billion USPS contract to replace old delivery vans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This contract busted, however I started writing this article before the deal busted - so don&amp;rsquo;t be surprised by the high numbers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I owned this stock for several years and wanna display my view of the company in this blog post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-usps-deal&#34;&gt;The USPS Deal&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;WKHS has a bad history with the USPS. E.g. a USPS driver was hurt during a prototype test. This isn&amp;rsquo;t the first USPS Deal on which WKHS had bid, more later on&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Competition for WKHS is Oshkosh (with Ford) and Karsan. Oshkosh had also offered a EV solution based on the Ford E-Transit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I thought Oshkosh has a very good chance because they are one of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Top_100_Contractors_of_the_U.S._federal_government&#34;&gt;Top 100 Contractors of the U.S. federal government&lt;/a&gt;. They have lots of experience while Workhorse never had such big contracts and would need help to produce lots of vehicles in a short time (at WKHS they assembled the vehicles via hand in the past, not automated in a factory)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oshkosh won the Deal, however the Valuation of this two stocks before that wasn&amp;rsquo;t on par. WKHS was way higher valuated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-valuation&#34;&gt;The Valuation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Would the Workhorse Group have won an 8 billion contract they probably won&amp;rsquo;t be able to produce all new vehicles in one year. But even if they would do that: Oshkosh had more than 8 billion revenue in 2019 and had a market cap of 6,78 billion USD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Workhorse had at 36,19 USD per stock a market cap of 4,36 billion. So the market cap already was in the area of a company with 8 billion revenue. I don&amp;rsquo;t see any reason why a higher valuation should be justified.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the valuation already had a winning of the contract and a really big EV bonus priced in. It may be fair compared to other EV companies like Tesla, but it definitely isn&amp;rsquo;t fair if you take good old school value figures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-cycle&#34;&gt;The Cycle&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Workhorse Stock is a Story Stock. This is not the first bid for a USPS Deal from Workhorse and you can see when they did bid on a big contract in the stock price history. Most of the times the big deals bust.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Current CEO Duane Hughes has a media background - perfect for marketing a story and if you read a few of the many short reports you see that this is the way with which the management had made money: Market the Story of the big deal and sell shares.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;future&#34;&gt;Future&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dubious YouTube Videos and bad finances should have been a big red flag for every common investor but the EV-Hyped Robinhood Community and Cathie Wood&amp;rsquo;s ARK Invest have pushed this stock without looking too much on the fundamentals and competition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So at the time of the writing the stock crashed after the announcement of the USPS Oshkosh Deal more than 47 percent to 16 USD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can&amp;rsquo;t say for sure if the stock will go up some time in the future again, BUT I am pretty sure if the stock goes up, it will be because some POSSIBLE Deal will get announced again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Make one thing clear: This wasn&amp;rsquo;t a traditional investment, this was a bet on a single Deal which made the most part of the valuation. That&amp;rsquo;s the reason I sold my shares - I don&amp;rsquo;t wanna make bets, I want to own profitable companies which share part of the profit with me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are in the stock market because of Bets, you probably should reconsider your Strategy. Because busted Stories like this can destroy your portfolio.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why Bumble is overvalued</title>
      <link>https://blog.m5e.de/post/why-bumble-is-overvalued/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.m5e.de/post/why-bumble-is-overvalued/</guid>
      <description>Yesterday Bumble had it&amp;rsquo;s initial public offering (IPO). The starting price was 43 USD, a valuation of more than 8 billion and it shot up to 76 USD, a valuation of over 13 billion.
Despite this high valuation, the company lastly made a net loss and only a few hundred million ($376.6 million) in revenue.
The Risk The current market for Tech, EV and Cannabis stocks is in a hype bubble.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;Yesterday Bumble had it&amp;rsquo;s initial public offering (IPO). The starting price was 43 USD, a valuation of more than 8 billion and it shot up to 76 USD, a valuation of over 13 billion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite this high valuation, the company lastly made a net loss and only a few hundred million ($376.6 million) in revenue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-risk&#34;&gt;The Risk&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The current market for Tech, EV and Cannabis stocks is in a hype bubble. I made profit with some overvalued stocks and currently sell these and rebalance my portfolio with more value stocks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But this is not the only risk. I&amp;rsquo;ve used Dating Apps since multiple months (I also made a &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.m5e.de/post/fighting-tinderplusplus-malware/&#34;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt; about a problem with Tinder) and I think the market will evolve:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;enter-the-world-of-facebook&#34;&gt;Enter the World of Facebook&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Facebook launched its own Dating service: Facebook Dating&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think this will dominate the market in a few years - why?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nearly all popular Dating Apps use Facebook Data / Login for registration and validation of the user
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Facebook already has data like Profile Photos, Workplace, Interests,&amp;hellip; which are important in the wold of online dating&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Facebook already has methods to validate profiles&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Facebook already has a bigger user base than all of the dating competition
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To me it seems like the user base of Facebook Dating is already bigger than the user base of Bumble in my local area&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve encountered no limits in swipes or other things
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All features which are premium on the competition Apps are free on Facebook&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve encountered no Ads in Facebook Dating&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I guess this depends on the individual, but I&amp;rsquo;ve got more matches in a few days on Facebook Dating than in multiple months on Bumble&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Facebook promotes social connections - you see who is Friends with other Facebook Friends of you on Facebook
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This adds validation - you trust the other side more that it is not a fake profile&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why should users register with Facebook on Third-Party-Apps if Facebook already provides a superior Dating experience?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Currently many people don&amp;rsquo;t know about Facebook Dating, but Facebook is a Advertising Platform with a giant user base - so it should be very easy to gain more and more people until the competition dies out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It looks like the Investors in Bumble aren&amp;rsquo;t aware that this big competitor is out there and the IPO money was needed for Bumble to have a chance fighting them.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On the 23andMe and VGAC Merger</title>
      <link>https://blog.m5e.de/post/on-the-23andme-and-vgac-merger/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.m5e.de/post/on-the-23andme-and-vgac-merger/</guid>
      <description>On the 4th February 2021 23andMe and VG Acquisition Corp announced that they will merge, bringing 23andMe into the public.
As VGAC is already tradable in the public market, the shares have skyrocketed to 19 USD. But this is crazy&amp;hellip;
Why this is crazy? First you should know that the initiators of a SPAC commonly have additional rights to e.g. buy additional shares. They also mostly pay 10 USD per share.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;On the 4th February 2021 23andMe and VG Acquisition Corp announced that they will merge, bringing 23andMe into the public.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As VGAC is already tradable in the public market, the shares have skyrocketed to 19 USD. But this is crazy&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-this-is-crazy&#34;&gt;Why this is crazy?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First you should know that the initiators of a SPAC commonly have additional rights to e.g. buy additional shares. They also mostly pay 10 USD per share. I don&amp;rsquo;t go more into detail here, but I want to talk about the shareholders which buy VGAC at the current 19 USD price WITHOUT additional rights like the initiators.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you look at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://vgacquisition.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/02/23andMe-Investor-Presentation.pdf&#34;&gt;Investor Presentation&lt;/a&gt; these VGAC shareholders will only get 11 % of the combined company! BUT the market cap of VGAC at 19.05 USD is 876.30 Mn!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So if you buy VGAC at 19 USD you don&amp;rsquo;t get 23andMe at a $3.5 billion valuation like Vigrin and the other investors - Nooo, you buy at a way higher price. 19 USD per VGAC share, 11 % of VGAC go into 23andMe would result into a nearly 8 billion valuation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To put it into comparison: At 19 USD per share you nearly buy at a valuation (8 billion) at which the institutional investors bought Ancestry ($4.7 billion) and 23andMe ($3.5 billion) combined.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also: 23andMe had declining revenue in the past years and does only make around 200 million revenue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You buy a business at a valuation at 8 billion which makes only around 200 million revenue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to buy 23andMe you should wait till the merger is done because the current VGAC market cap is way too high considering existing VGAC shareholders will only get a little part of the combined company.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A alternative investment Idea could be OraSure Technologies Inc - these are the producers of the diagnostic testing kits which are used by 23andMe and Ancestry. Current market cap only 989,83 Mio USD, the sales have declined from 181,74 Mio in 2018 to 154,60 Mio in 2019 but looks like a fair or even cheap valuation to me.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Apple environmental friendly?</title>
      <link>https://blog.m5e.de/post/apple-environmental-friendly/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.m5e.de/post/apple-environmental-friendly/</guid>
      <description>Why Apple Products aren&amp;rsquo;t as environmentally problematic as many believe. Apple bashing is popular these days. Louis Rossmann, Hugh Jeffreys and others are talking about repair issues on YouTube, Mark Zuckerberg sees Apple as an unfair competitor and Xiaomi mocks Apple for Not Including Charger and then does the same.
So in this world where Apple bashing is popular I wanna tell you my opinion.
I bought my first new Apple Products this year (primarily caused by the impressive performance of the M1), but I already have used used Apple Devices for a longer period.</description>
      <content>&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-apple-products-arent-as-environmentally-problematic-as-many-believe&#34;&gt;Why Apple Products aren&amp;rsquo;t as environmentally problematic as many believe.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apple bashing is popular these days. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/user/rossmanngroup&#34;&gt;Louis Rossmann&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/user/hughydo&#34;&gt;Hugh Jeffreys&lt;/a&gt; and others are talking about repair issues on YouTube, Mark Zuckerberg sees Apple as an &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2021-01-28/facebook-ceo-ramps-up-apple-attack-weighs-antitrust-suit&#34;&gt;unfair competitor&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://gizmodo.com/xiaomi-made-fun-of-apple-for-not-including-charger-in-b-1845954366&#34;&gt;Xiaomi mocks Apple&lt;/a&gt; for Not Including Charger and then does the same.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So in this world where Apple bashing is popular I wanna tell you my opinion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I bought my first new Apple Products this year (primarily caused by the impressive performance of the M1), but I already have used used Apple Devices for a longer period.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am by no means an Apple Fanboy. My main daily drivers where Android, Linux (Arch Linux and Debian) and Windows devices and I will continue to use these devices alongside my new shiny Apple stuff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Besides that I am a Xiaomi, Fairphone and Lenovo shareholder and currently no Apple shareholder - so my financial interest is the success of the competition, not the success of Apple.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After clearing my position on Apple as a company I wanna share you why I think Apple is not as environmentally problematic as many blame them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;environmental-friendly&#34;&gt;Environmental friendly&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are some points which make Apple devices kinda environmental friendly:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Higher price encourages people to use it longer and not replace it as fast as Android smartphones&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The high price also lets more people try to repair it than cheap Androids
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some of the competitors have more expensive replacement parts than a new mobile phone (think of curved displays)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Longer lasting software support&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Smaller battery which uses less resources from the environment&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Smaller range of products - repair shops can concentrate on some products instead of trying to have replacement parts for a really big Android or Windows device world&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;problems&#34;&gt;Problems&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of these Problems do not only affect Apple devices, Androids have the same issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Apple seem to pair everything - from the TouchID over Display, Camera, even the Battery - and limits replacement parts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Only special devices can copy this pairing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It becomes more difficult to open the products&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Many things like display and battery are glued and need special devices which work with the optimal heat&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Many parts or schematics which could be used to repair devices aren&amp;rsquo;t even offered by Apple&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;advantages-over-android&#34;&gt;Advantages over Android&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Longer software support (even cool programs like Android One are getting less popular)
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Android One offers a guaranteed time of getting updates but many hardware partners are &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.techradar.com/news/xiaomi-may-have-ditched-the-android-one-program&#34;&gt;moving away&lt;/a&gt; from this program&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Even with Project Treble which makes it easier to offer Updates for Android devices many OEMs still don&amp;rsquo;t do this over many years&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Less battery usage (so smaller batteries and less used Lithium) but better performance thanks to a better processor architecture&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Less diversify, thus a shorter list of replacement parts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Repair knowledge concentration on a smaller list of devices, thus better support against the big Android or Windows world&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Advantages are often not really intended but a by-product&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lots of Bashing - but Apple has environmental advantages over many other producers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Many people in social media blame only Apple but the competition is not really better&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wanna note that if you really have a problem with repairability then you should buy something like a Fairphone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;BUT you should know that you can get much more performance for your money from Xiaomi or Apple and you can buy used Xiaomi phones with a better performance than a Fairphone cheaper as some of the Fairphone parts costs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have repaired Xiaomi phones in the past, so it is not impossible. Displays for low-end Xiaomi devices do only cost around 20 EUR -  that&amp;rsquo;s 4.5 times cheaper than a Fairphone 3 Display!!! (For the 90 EUR cost of a Fairphone Display you can even get a new phone from Xiaomi)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Someone who buys a expensive product will be more likely to try to repair it than someone who buys a cheap product and unfortunately even companies which were known to offer repairable devices like Lenovo are doing things like soldering more and more RAM onto the Laptop instead of using slots&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Comparison of Email Hosting Possibilities</title>
      <link>https://blog.m5e.de/post/comparison-of-email-hosting-possibilities/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.m5e.de/post/comparison-of-email-hosting-possibilities/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve hosted my own Mailserver in various configurations since more than 6 years now. Since then I&amp;rsquo;ve taken multiple breaks from hosting it myself and explored other solutions for hosting emails with your own domain names.
Because my own Mailserver has lately problems (downtimes) I wanna explore other possibilities of hosting my email addresses.
So let&amp;rsquo;s take a look&amp;hellip;
Self-hosting (VPS, Tools like Mailcow, Mailu, etc) You simply setup a Mailserver with software like Mailcow, Mailu or Mail-in-a-Box on a virtual Server and manage it yourself.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve hosted my own Mailserver in various configurations since more than 6 years now. Since then I&amp;rsquo;ve taken multiple breaks from hosting it myself and explored other solutions for hosting emails with your own domain names.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because my own Mailserver has lately problems (downtimes) I wanna explore other possibilities of hosting my email addresses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So let&amp;rsquo;s take a look&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;self-hosting-vps-tools-like-mailcow-mailu-etc&#34;&gt;Self-hosting (VPS, Tools like Mailcow, Mailu, etc)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You simply setup a Mailserver with software like Mailcow, Mailu or Mail-in-a-Box on a virtual Server and manage it yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pros:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You have the control&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Unlimited domains&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Unlimited mailboxes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cheaper than most alternatives if you don&amp;rsquo;t look at the time you need for setup and maintenance&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cons:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Most cheap VPS don&amp;rsquo;t offer a lot of space and if you subtract the OS and installed software, then your space for mail is very limited&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You need to invest a lot of time&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You need a good spec VPS because Mailserver software and SPAM protection are performance intensive&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Small VPS are often targeted by criminals and protection isn&amp;rsquo;t very easy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is what I&amp;rsquo;ve done the most of the time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the past this was very straightforward if you know how to setup and secure a mailserver but I&amp;rsquo;ve lately problems with things like DDoS and Brute Force Attacks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=24154524&#34;&gt;question&lt;/a&gt; from me on Hacker News was even so heavily voted that it was for a short time on the front page of HN - so this seems to be a problem for other people too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;pawnmail&#34;&gt;Pawnmail&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This service doesn&amp;rsquo;t exist anymore but I wanna mention it because it was one of the few free providers where you can get mailboxes for your own domains.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AFAIK that service doesn&amp;rsquo;t exist anymore because it was targeted by spammers and had problems with attacks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;zoho-mail&#34;&gt;Zoho Mail&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The free plan supports one domain with up to five users and has a 5GB/User and 25MB attachment limit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unusable for me because IMAP/ POP/ Active Sync are not included in the free plan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Indian company, the CEO seems to support Hindu nationalism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;yandex-mail&#34;&gt;Yandex Mail&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The biggest player in my comparison. Offers 10 GB of storage, up to 1000 users and support for custom domains for free.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It seems like the only problem is that you have to trust a Russian company.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;mxroute&#34;&gt;MXroute&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Has various plans for custom Domain Email Hosting. All plans include support for unlimited Domains and unlimited Email Accounts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Especially the Black Friday deals seem to be pretty good every year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;US company, interestingly the Founder has worked for Christian Institutions - so both - the CEOs of Zoho and MXroute seem to be religious persons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;mailcheapco&#34;&gt;Mailcheap.co&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cheap Hosting Provider for custom Domain Email, comparable to MXroute but it has more bad reviews than MXroute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;migadu&#34;&gt;Migadu&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the HN Post to this Article &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=25201493&#34;&gt;someone mentioned&lt;/a&gt; Migadu.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Migadu is the only provider on this comparison from Switzerland and the pricing is more expensive compared to the US providers&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So you pay more but your data is probably also more secure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;postaleio&#34;&gt;postale.io&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;French provider, offers a free plan which includes one domain, 2 mailboxes, 3 aliases and 1 GB per mailbox.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately it seems like the cheapest hosting possibilities are either trusting a Russian company which government maybe spies on you, trusting a US company which is also obliged to let the government spy on you or to go to an Indian company which is run by a Hindu nationalism supporter&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hosting your own server isn&amp;rsquo;t the cheapest option but you are more in control.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know there are privacy focused providers like ProtonMail or Fastmail out there but the cost of those services are way higher than the providers I mentioned at the time of this writing. (Especially if you want more than one mailbox. Most popular services are on a pay per-user basis, but MXroute, Mailcheap, Yandex and your own VPS are more on a pay per-storage / resources plan)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I think I will split my domains to various services - in that way no government has all of my information and I am more immune to downtimes.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fighting the Tinder&#43;&#43; Malware</title>
      <link>https://blog.m5e.de/post/fighting-tinderplusplus-malware/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.m5e.de/post/fighting-tinderplusplus-malware/</guid>
      <description>People who search for love are more vulnerable than happy couples. Especially people who lost their Tinder Account because Tinder has banned them.
There is a malware out there which targets exactly this kind of people. If you search for &amp;ldquo;unban tinder&amp;rdquo; on Google and or YouTube you find many videos and sites which recommend the &amp;ldquo;Tinder++&amp;rdquo; App.
Tinder++ aims to bring you free Tinder Gold and unban your Account. People on sites and videos which recommend the App talk that the Tinder ban is only per Device and they found a way to get around this ban.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;People who search for love are more vulnerable than happy couples. Especially people who lost their Tinder Account because Tinder has banned them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a malware out there which targets exactly this kind of people. If you search for &amp;ldquo;unban tinder&amp;rdquo; on Google and or YouTube you find many videos and sites which recommend the &amp;ldquo;Tinder++&amp;rdquo; App.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tinder++ aims to bring you free Tinder Gold and unban your Account. People on sites and videos which recommend the App talk that the Tinder ban is only per Device and they found a way to get around this ban.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Tinder++ is no App you can get from the Google Play Store or even F-Droid. No! You have to download the App from suspicious sites &amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I found this Scheme and I wanted to Stop it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am the kind of people which look at the Header of Spam-Mails and report the sender or linked URLs to the Domain registrar, Hoster, DNS-Provider and Blocklists. Because we live in a civilized world and well known Provider don&amp;rsquo;t wanna host Spammers or other Assholes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;but-how-did-i-fight-them&#34;&gt;But how did I fight them?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I downloaded the file and uploaded it to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.virustotal.com/gui/file/808a2ac6b6fbf6d0d8cb8b0ab1996faf538b380485955e09ca78a74516790f17/summary&#34;&gt;VirusTotal&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This showed that the file is clearly harmful&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I reported the YouTube Videos and made a comment with the VirusTotal Link and a warning about the App&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I checked the Whois Data which gave me the information that the site uses Namecheap as Domain Provider and Cloudflare as DNS-Provider&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I reported the Domain to Namecheap and Cloudflare
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Namecheap replied after checking the site that they can do nothing and I need to contact Cloudflare (which I already did)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I created a Hosts-File with the domains and added my Blocklist to my pfBlockerNG instance (so you can&amp;rsquo;t access the malware in my network anymore)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I contacted Tinder and informed them too&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;notes&#34;&gt;Notes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The sites seems to only show you the APK-File if you visit it via a Android Smartphone, so they seem to check the User-Agent, Resolution or something else&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I think you would be surprised how many provider really look into SPAM / Malware sites and try to do something. I have written emails about cases like this or simple SPAM cases over Days and the provider I contacted often contacted additional involved provider.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you get a SPAM or phishing mail you should report them because the spammers often use a legal provider in their chain and that provider often is a victim himself (because he is used for illegal activity which puts him in a bad light)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The site seems to do various other scam surveys too: &lt;a href=&#34;https://silzee.com/jailbreak/apphacks/&#34;&gt;https://silzee.com/jailbreak/apphacks/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;current-status&#34;&gt;Current status&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the time of this writing the site which distributes the malware is still out there. I haven&amp;rsquo;t received any notification about the current status from either YouTube or Cloudflare. (And I honestly don&amp;rsquo;t think I get a reply from YouTube - I mean even Woz needed to sue YouTube because they didn&amp;rsquo;t reply to him &amp;hellip;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But please don&amp;rsquo;t get this wrong! Many provider do something if they can prove that there is something illegal going on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;update&#34;&gt;Update&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Head of Trust &amp;amp; Safety at Cloudflare (Justin) reacted to my Tweet but hasn&amp;rsquo;t found &amp;ldquo;definitive proof it&amp;rsquo;s malicious&amp;rdquo;. I hope he looks a little bit closer because I see a site full of scam.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Benchmarking Go, Crystal, Python and JavaScript</title>
      <link>https://blog.m5e.de/post/benchmarking-go-crystal-python-and-js/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.m5e.de/post/benchmarking-go-crystal-python-and-js/</guid>
      <description>Benford&amp;rsquo;s Law After watching a Netflix documentary about Benford&amp;rsquo;s Law (&amp;ldquo;connected&amp;rdquo; Season 1 Episode 4 &amp;ldquo;Digits&amp;rdquo;), I got really interested in it because it can help detect fraud in e.g. balance sheets. So I searched my favorite programming languages and detected that there is no npm Package for checking Benford&amp;rsquo;s Law.
Sooo &amp;hellip; Long story short: I created nearly identical libraries for doing a Benford&amp;rsquo;s Law check in JavaScript, Go and Crystal.</description>
      <content>&lt;h2 id=&#34;benfords-law&#34;&gt;Benford&amp;rsquo;s Law&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After watching a Netflix documentary about Benford&amp;rsquo;s Law (&amp;ldquo;connected&amp;rdquo; Season 1 Episode 4 &amp;ldquo;Digits&amp;rdquo;), I got really interested in it because it can help detect fraud in e.g. balance sheets. So I searched my favorite programming languages and detected that there is no npm Package for checking Benford&amp;rsquo;s Law.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sooo &amp;hellip; Long story short: I created nearly identical libraries for doing a Benford&amp;rsquo;s Law check in JavaScript, Go and Crystal. My inspiration was from a Python library - so the algorithm of these libraries is nearly identical. There are some catches like I used many different math libraries for calculating chi-square and some of these libraries offer addition information, others not &amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I think this gives us a good example of a algorithm which is implemented in different programming languages and can be benchmarked. That&amp;rsquo;s what I wanna do in this post: Comparing the Benford&amp;rsquo;s Law check in different Languages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;testing-the-performance&#34;&gt;Testing the Performance&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Repo with Source Code: &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/CMiksche/benford-benchmark&#34;&gt;https://github.com/CMiksche/benford-benchmark&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Language &amp;amp; Version&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;GitHub Repo of Library&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Performance&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Python 3.8.5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/target/huntlib&#34;&gt;huntlib&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1,86 secs&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Crystal 0.35.1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/CMiksche/benfordslaw.cr&#34;&gt;benfordslaw.cr&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;14,20 millis&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Go 1.15&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/CMiksche/benford&#34;&gt;benford&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;7,03 millis&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;JS (node) v14.8.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/CMiksche/benfordslaw&#34;&gt;benfordslaw&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;164,71 millis&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I didn&amp;rsquo;t expected that big difference. Go is clearly the winner here and that with big distance to the other implementations. One reason why Python took so long may be that the used library shows additional information but I don&amp;rsquo;t think Python could compete with the other implementations if the library wouldn&amp;rsquo;t show more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is also noteworthy that Go is very very fast compiling. Crystal isn&amp;rsquo;t even in the area of the Go compile time.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Switching to Hugo</title>
      <link>https://blog.m5e.de/post/switching-to-hugo/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.m5e.de/post/switching-to-hugo/</guid>
      <description>Moving to Hugo I started this blog as my first blog using a static website generator. Back then I used what everyone else was using: Jekyll.
But Jekyll has it problems. I don&amp;rsquo;t use Ruby for anything else and the management of the dependencies / ruby versions / etc of my static blog was too much for me.
I blog way more often in german on my other WordPress sites and one of the main reasons is that it is easier and Jekyll wasn&amp;rsquo;t as easy as I expected.</description>
      <content>&lt;h2 id=&#34;moving-to-hugo&#34;&gt;Moving to Hugo&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started this blog as my first blog using a static website generator. Back then I used what everyone else was using: Jekyll.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Jekyll has it problems. I don&amp;rsquo;t use Ruby for anything else and the management of the dependencies / ruby versions / etc of my &lt;strong&gt;static&lt;/strong&gt; blog was too much for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I blog way more often in german on my other WordPress sites and one of the main reasons is that it is easier and Jekyll wasn&amp;rsquo;t as easy as I expected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I switched to Hugo today. Hugo is written in Go and available as a binary - so no more dependencies! Yay! Its also faster! Yay again!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But then I installed a theme which required npm Packages &amp;hellip; So let&amp;rsquo;s see how happy I will be managing this dependencies &amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;notes-about-url-rewrite&#34;&gt;Notes about URL rewrite&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So there are many articles about switching from Hugo to Jekyll out there. Basically the &lt;code&gt;hugo import jekyll jekyll_root_path target_path&lt;/code&gt; command from Hugo converts your posts and then you need to manually edit the config, install a theme and copy your custom pages to &amp;lsquo;content&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But one thing was missing what no other article I found mentioned: What if you want to have the same URL Scheme like Jekyll had in your older posts (so links to them still work) but use the default Hugo URL Scheme for new posts?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is possible! You can define custom URLs for each post. My first blog post looks like that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-markdown&#34; data-lang=&#34;markdown&#34;&gt;---
date: &amp;#34;2017-02-14T20:03:23Z&amp;#34;
title: First try of Jekyll
tags: [jekyll, first, post]
url: &amp;#34;jekyll/first/post/2017/02/14/first-try-of-jekyll.html&amp;#34;
---
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;So if you look at the URL of that old post it has the old style from Jekyll but this post about switching to Hugo has the new URL Scheme.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Forget Bash, take Python!</title>
      <link>https://blog.m5e.de/bash/script/python/linux/2020/05/22/forget-bash-take-python.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.m5e.de/bash/script/python/linux/2020/05/22/forget-bash-take-python.html</guid>
      <description>I wrote bash scripts for several years now. You can find old bash scripts of mine on GitHub but most of them aren&amp;rsquo;t maintained anymore - and I have a reason for that.
But before I give you my reasons for not using many bash scripts anymore, lets look at the benefits of bash:
 It super easy and you basically already can it if you write Linux / BSD commands There are frameworks out now which give you advanced features like testing It works out of the box on nearly every Linux / BSD system  Okay - sounds good - so what&amp;rsquo;s my problem?</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;I wrote bash scripts for several years now. You can find old bash scripts of mine on GitHub but most of them aren&amp;rsquo;t maintained anymore - and I have a reason for that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But before I give you my reasons for not using many bash scripts anymore, lets look at the benefits of bash:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It super easy and you basically already can it if you write Linux / BSD commands&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are frameworks out now which give you advanced features like testing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It works out of the box on nearly every Linux / BSD system&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay - sounds good - so what&amp;rsquo;s my problem?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bash is limited. E.g. it doesn&amp;rsquo;t work out of the box in Windows and I switched my default shell in Linux to fish. But let&amp;rsquo;s break down a few points why Bash isn&amp;rsquo;t optimal for me:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You tend to write platform specific code - e.g. I switched from Debian to Arch Linux and had to replace the &lt;code&gt;apt-get&lt;/code&gt; commands with &lt;code&gt;pacman&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I use fish as default shell. You can use Bash-Scripts with fish, but it&amp;rsquo;s more complicated &amp;hellip;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Linux isn&amp;rsquo;t my only operating system - I run Windows and macOS machines as well.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I love features of higher level programming languages like Python.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And how does Python solve this problem?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It runs out of the box on many Linux systems&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s cross-platform - the same code can run under Linux, Windows, macOS, &amp;hellip; but you also can check the current system and write platform specific code for that&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is also super easy and makes fun&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Testing and more advanced features are build in - no need to install packages&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Like bash, it is already used for automating tasks in many systems (so you can find tons of help online)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can simply access the operating system&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Distribution is also very simple - just create a package and pip can install it from the PyPI, private registry or a Git-Repo&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Languages like Go would also be interesting for automating tasks in your Linux system but Go has things like pointers and types. Python is more similar to Bash - very simple without advanced topics like types or pointers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I created many python scripts for things which solved bash scripts before. And my python scripts all have unit tests and detect the current running operating system. Whereas my bash scripts only worked on Debian systems do my python scripts work on all my used operating systems. So it has saved me a lot of work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I also continue to use little bash scripts for simple tasks like &amp;ldquo;open this on startup&amp;rdquo; - I think it&amp;rsquo;s important to be aware, that higher level languages like python have a big benefit if you want to switch your system but use the same scripts.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Gitea Auto Update Script</title>
      <link>https://blog.m5e.de/gitea/update/upgrade/bash/script/2018/11/26/gitea-auto-update-script.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Nov 2018 21:24:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.m5e.de/gitea/update/upgrade/bash/script/2018/11/26/gitea-auto-update-script.html</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;m a Gitea user for a long time now. Gitea is a nice application to build your own light and fast version of git hosting services like GitHub or GitLab.
Gitea has one problem thought. It doesn&amp;rsquo;t update automatically. A issue for that is open nearly 2 years: https://github.com/go-gitea/gitea/issues/518#issuecomment-441742904
If there is one thing that I really hate, it is that a security sensible web application doesn&amp;rsquo;t update automatically. Because of that I have begun to write a update script for Gitea before 4 months.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m a Gitea user for a long time now. Gitea is a nice application to build your own light and fast version of git hosting services like GitHub or GitLab.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gitea has one problem thought. It doesn&amp;rsquo;t update automatically. A issue for that is open nearly 2 years: &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/go-gitea/gitea/issues/518#issuecomment-441742904&#34;&gt;https://github.com/go-gitea/gitea/issues/518#issuecomment-441742904&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If there is one thing that I really hate, it is that a security sensible web application doesn&amp;rsquo;t update automatically. Because of that I have begun to write a update script for Gitea before 4 months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That script has updated my Gitea instance multiple times now and as I can see, that many users have the same problem (a german blog post from me is my most visited article from outside germany), I want to show you my solution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;warning&#34;&gt;Warning&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned - I am no fan of manual upgrades - because of that I write many auto update scripts for my own systems. This scripts often haven&amp;rsquo;t been tested on other systems and may contain ugly code. 
I am open for the creation of issues or pull requests which optimise my code. You should definitely check the code out and make sure to review it before using it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some creators - e.g. the person behind Kanboard - have a strong option against auto updates. There are good reasons for that too - you may not want to crash your application because of a faulty upgrade. I recommend auto updates only if you create auto backups, too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-script&#34;&gt;The Script&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have published the actual version to GitHub: &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/CMiksche/gitea-auto-update&#34;&gt;https://github.com/CMiksche/gitea-auto-update&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The script was made for a Debian and Arch Linux Systems - I haven&amp;rsquo;t tested it on other systems, but you will definitely encounter errors if you want to use it on Windows, MacOS or a Linux System without systemd (I make bash calls to restart the Gitea service).
You may need to modify the script to work on your system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the Gitea upgrade changes the template files the automatic update may will destroy your custom design because it is a really simple script and doesn&amp;rsquo;t check that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;how-to-use-it&#34;&gt;How to use it&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The usage of my script is easy (please read the paragraphs over this first - it won&amp;rsquo;t work without modifying it if you have no gitea service or no systemd):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Install my script on the system:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;pip install gitea-auto-update&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Create a settings.ini file:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Gitea]
site=https://your-gitea-instance.com/api/v1/version
apiUrl=https://api.github.com/repos/go-gitea/gitea/releases/latest
system=linux-amd64
file=/usr/local/bin/gitea
tmpDir=/tmp/
buildFromSource=
sourceDir=
logFile=update.log
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Change the variables in the settings.ini file&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Enter the command &lt;code&gt;gite-auto-update --settings=/path/to/settings.ini&lt;/code&gt; in your command line to test the first upgrade&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you want to schedule your updates, edit your &lt;code&gt;/etc/crontab&lt;/code&gt; file and add a call to the script&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s it. Please write a issue if my script doesn&amp;rsquo;t works. I am caring if people want to use my script ;-)&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>FreeBSD: nvidia-driver installation</title>
      <link>https://blog.m5e.de/freebsd/nvidia-driver/installation/2017/11/19/freebsd-nvidia-driver-installation.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 Nov 2017 15:59:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.m5e.de/freebsd/nvidia-driver/installation/2017/11/19/freebsd-nvidia-driver-installation.html</guid>
      <description>After installing FreeBSD to my workstation, I wanted a desktop environment. I&amp;rsquo;ve installed gnome3 after reading the official documentation https://www.freebsd.org/doc/handbook/x11-wm.html.
But nothing has worked. So, I installed the nvidia-driver for my two GPUs. The first documentation I&amp;rsquo;ve found is from &amp;ldquo;7.3-RELEASE&amp;rdquo;: https://docs.freebsd.org/doc/7.3-RELEASE/usr/share/doc/en/articles/compiz-fusion/nvidia-setup.html. (I use 11.1-RELEASE)
Don&amp;rsquo;t use that documentation to make your settings in /boot/loader.conf! There stands:
nvidia_load=&amp;quot;YES&amp;quot; And that&amp;rsquo;s simply not right for the newest driver!
You should enter the following line:</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;After installing FreeBSD to my workstation, I wanted a desktop environment. I&amp;rsquo;ve installed gnome3 after reading the official documentation &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.freebsd.org/doc/handbook/x11-wm.html&#34;&gt;https://www.freebsd.org/doc/handbook/x11-wm.html&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But nothing has worked. So, I installed the nvidia-driver for my two GPUs. The first documentation I&amp;rsquo;ve found is from &amp;ldquo;7.3-RELEASE&amp;rdquo;: &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.freebsd.org/doc/7.3-RELEASE/usr/share/doc/en/articles/compiz-fusion/nvidia-setup.html&#34;&gt;https://docs.freebsd.org/doc/7.3-RELEASE/usr/share/doc/en/articles/compiz-fusion/nvidia-setup.html&lt;/a&gt;. (I use 11.1-RELEASE)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t use that documentation to make your settings in &lt;code&gt;/boot/loader.conf&lt;/code&gt;! There stands:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;nvidia_load=&amp;quot;YES&amp;quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that&amp;rsquo;s simply not right for the newest driver!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You should enter the following line:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;nvidia-modeset_load=&amp;quot;YES&amp;quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After that and using nvidia-xconfig to create the Xorg-Config file, my system works now.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>FreeBSD and Windows 10 Dual-Boot</title>
      <link>https://blog.m5e.de/freebsd/windows10/dual-boot/2017/11/19/freebsd-windows10-dual-boot.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 Nov 2017 15:45:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.m5e.de/freebsd/windows10/dual-boot/2017/11/19/freebsd-windows10-dual-boot.html</guid>
      <description>Yesterday I have installed FreeBSD alongside to a existing Windows 10 instance on my Workstation. Today, I want to show you how to do it.
Prerequisites My setup is a SSD with Windows 10 already installed and more than 100 GB free space.
Procedure Install FreeBSD normally (but pay attention to use the free space for FreeBSD during the partitioning).
After the install, you can switch to the shell to take final settings.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;Yesterday I have installed FreeBSD alongside to a existing Windows 10 instance on my Workstation. Today, I want to show you how to do it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;prerequisites&#34;&gt;Prerequisites&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My setup is a SSD with Windows 10 already installed and more than 100 GB free space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;procedure&#34;&gt;Procedure&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Install FreeBSD normally (but pay attention to use the free space for FreeBSD during the partitioning).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the install, you can switch to the shell to take final settings. There you can enter the following command:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;boot0cfg -B ada0
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s it. Reboot and everything should work fine ;-)&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>APU2C4 - LED blinks 5 times ...</title>
      <link>https://blog.m5e.de/apu2c4/blink/led/2017/11/16/apu2c4-blinks-5-times.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Nov 2017 16:03:23 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.m5e.de/apu2c4/blink/led/2017/11/16/apu2c4-blinks-5-times.html</guid>
      <description>I bought a APU2C4 Board (from the swiss company &amp;ldquo;PC Engines GmbH&amp;rdquo;) and multiple components because I want to build a custom pfSense router.
I&amp;rsquo;ve ordered the device several weeks ago and haven&amp;rsquo;t used it until now. That&amp;rsquo;s because I made a few mistakes (which I want to write now):
First  Mistake: I used a power supply with 12V and 2A from china. Visible by: The LED on the back of the device blinks 5 times - then no more again.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;I bought a APU2C4 Board (from the swiss company &amp;ldquo;PC Engines GmbH&amp;rdquo;) and multiple components because I want to build a custom pfSense router.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve ordered the device several weeks ago and haven&amp;rsquo;t used it until now. That&amp;rsquo;s because I made a few mistakes (which I want to write now):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;first&#34;&gt;First&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mistake: I used a power supply with 12V and 2A from china.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Visible by: The LED on the back of the device blinks 5 times - then no more again.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Solution: Use a 12V and 3A power supply.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;second&#34;&gt;Second:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mistake: I used a serial cable with Prolific PL2303 Chip and another serial cable with a Gender Changer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Visible by: I couldn&amp;rsquo;t connect to the device.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Solution: Don&amp;rsquo;t use PL2303 Chips and Gender Changer! The following Chips are supported: FTDI / FT232RL and Silicon Labs CP2104&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the way: The support of pc-engines is really fast - great customer experience &amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My new serial cable with FT232RL chip hasn&amp;rsquo;t arrived yet. I will write more about that device when i encounter new errors &amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>First try of Jekyll</title>
      <link>https://blog.m5e.de/jekyll/first/post/2017/02/14/first-try-of-jekyll.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Feb 2017 20:03:23 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.m5e.de/jekyll/first/post/2017/02/14/first-try-of-jekyll.html</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve already using different blog systems like WordPress and Ghost, but this is my try to start a blog in english about personal and development topics with Jekyll.
Maybe is the domain not my best choice (.de is the domain for germany), but as I haven&amp;rsquo;t any project on it, I will use it.
I will be using GitHub as hosting service. That will have a few great side effects: you can download my whole blog via git clone, in the same way you could mirror my blog and if you want to notified when a new change happens, you could subscribe my Blog via the &amp;ldquo;Watch&amp;rdquo; Function of GitHub.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve already using different blog systems like WordPress and Ghost, but this is my try to start a blog in english about personal and development topics with Jekyll.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe is the domain not my best choice (.de is the domain for germany), but as I haven&amp;rsquo;t any project on it, I will use it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will be using GitHub as hosting service. That will have a few great side effects: you can download my whole blog via git clone, in the same way you could mirror my blog and if you want to notified when a new change happens, you could subscribe my Blog via the &amp;ldquo;Watch&amp;rdquo; Function of GitHub.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t like limits. Because of that, I will only push the &lt;code&gt;_site&lt;/code&gt; directory to my GitHub Repo. (In that way I can use custom plugins in Jekyll)&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Contact &amp; Imprint</title>
      <link>https://blog.m5e.de/contact/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.m5e.de/contact/</guid>
      <description>This is Christoph Daniel Miksche&amp;rsquo;s blog in english. He also offers a german blog at http://christoph.miksche.org.
Legal Disclosure Information in accordance with section 5 TMG
Christoph Miksche
Forststraße 2
97500 Ebelsbach
Contact Telephone: 0176 82532907
E-Mail: christoph[at]miksche[dot]org
Disclaimer Accountability for content The contents of our pages have been created with the utmost care. However, we cannot guarantee the contents&#39; accuracy, completeness or topicality. According to statutory provisions, we are furthermore responsible for our own content on these web pages.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;This is Christoph Daniel Miksche&amp;rsquo;s blog in english. He also offers a german blog at &lt;a href=&#34;http://christoph.miksche.org&#34;&gt;http://christoph.miksche.org&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;legal-disclosure&#34;&gt;Legal Disclosure&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Information in accordance with section 5 TMG&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Christoph Miksche&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Forststraße 2&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;97500 Ebelsbach&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;contact&#34;&gt;Contact&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Telephone: 0176 82532907&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;E-Mail: christoph[at]miksche[dot]org&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;disclaimer&#34;&gt;Disclaimer&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;accountability-for-content&#34;&gt;Accountability for content&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The contents of our pages have been created with the utmost care. However, we cannot guarantee the contents&#39; accuracy, completeness or topicality. According to statutory provisions, we are furthermore responsible for our own content on these web pages. In this context, please note that we are accordingly not obliged to monitor merely the transmitted or saved information of third parties, or investigate circumstances pointing to illegal activity. Our obligations to remove or block the use of information under generally applicable laws remain unaffected by this as per §§ 8 to 10 of the Telemedia Act (TMG).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;accountability-for-links&#34;&gt;Accountability for links&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Responsibility for the content of external links (to web pages of third parties) lies solely with the operators of the linked pages. No violations were evident to us at the time of linking. Should any legal infringement become known to us, we will remove the respective link immediately.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;copyright&#34;&gt;Copyright&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our web pages and their contents are subject to German copyright law. Unless expressly permitted by law (§ 44a et seq. of the copyright law), every form of utilizing, reproducing or processing works subject to copyright protection on our web pages requires the prior consent of the respective owner of the rights. Individual reproductions of a work are allowed only for private use, so must not serve either directly or indirectly for earnings. Unauthorized utilization of copyrighted works is punishable (§ 106 of the copyright law).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Quelle: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.twigg.de/&#34;&gt;impressum generator - twigg.de&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>