<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>gTLD on M5E&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>https://blog.m5e.de/tags/gTLD/</link>
    <description>Recent content in gTLD on M5E&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 05 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://blog.m5e.de/tags/gTLD/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Investing in Domains</title>
      <link>https://blog.m5e.de/post/investing-in-domains/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.m5e.de/post/investing-in-domains/</guid>
      <description>Since I started creating websites at a young age, I always tried to have good domain names for my projects. I also sold a few - that&amp;rsquo;s why I want to cover this topic today.
A good domain name can be worth quite a bit. Some Domains were sold for multiple millions.
But unfortunately, Investing in Domains isn&amp;rsquo;t quite so easy as you think. I bought at least 45 different domain names and selling them is really hard.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;Since I started creating websites at a young age, I always tried to have good domain names for my projects. I also sold a few - that&amp;rsquo;s why I want to cover this topic today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A good domain name can be worth quite a bit. Some Domains were sold for multiple millions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But unfortunately, Investing in Domains isn&amp;rsquo;t quite so easy as you think. I bought at least 45 different domain names and selling them is really hard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-it-is-hard&#34;&gt;Why it is hard&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;costs&#34;&gt;Costs&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You have to pay monthly for your domain name. So owning a domain has a certain fix cost.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How much you pay depends on the ending of your domain. Because the Top-level domain (TLD), which is the last part of your domain name, is normally operated by a company. This company can decide how much a registration costs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But that&amp;rsquo;s not the only cost. Normally, you don&amp;rsquo;t buy your domain directly from the TLD operator. You buy them from a registry, which itself is a customer of the TLD operator.
This registry also has costs and wants to make a profit, so they obviously ask for a higher price than they pay the operator.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(BTW: Operating such a TLD is also not such a great business - I wrote a &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.m5e.de/post/analyzing-the-profitability-of-gtld-registry-operators/&#34;&gt;blog post&lt;/a&gt; about that too)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;selling-it&#34;&gt;Selling it&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Until now, I only sold two domains. During a period of more than a decade domain ownership.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I think it is self explaining that I don&amp;rsquo;t buy domain names for selling, but because I need them for my own project ideas and my company. In total, owing the domains has cost me more than I earned from them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are multiple ways to sell a domain. I had multiple offers from people who contacted me directly. That means they found e.g. my Twitter handle or my email address and send me a message asking if I would be willing to sell the domain to them. Some of them even wanted to buy whole projects from me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other way of selling domains is using specialized Websites like sedo.com, dan.com, Domain Forums, Facebook Groups or even the registries themselves (Namecheap offers customers also to sell their domains on the Namecheap marketplace for example)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did both ways and unfortunately even if you use a marketplace which promotes your domain name it&amp;rsquo;s very hard because not every customer is interested in all domains - they search for a specific domain fitting their business, and you have to have the luck of encountering the customer who actually needs your domain name for his business.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;is-it-worth-it&#34;&gt;Is it worth it?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For most of the people: No!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cost of having a domain name is in most cases more expensive than the potential profit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some companies have specialized in reselling domain names (Tucows Inc. is one of the most popular examples). But most of these specialists also try to earn money with Advertisements on the domain names and with Economies of Scale.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They usually get a ton of domain names way cheaper than normal customers and also have way more data about which domain names have a higher chance to be bought.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So this is a hard market, and the average John Doe should only buy a domain name for this own usage.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Analyzing the profitability of gTLD registry operators</title>
      <link>https://blog.m5e.de/post/analyzing-the-profitability-of-gtld-registry-operators/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.m5e.de/post/analyzing-the-profitability-of-gtld-registry-operators/</guid>
      <description>I am a very big DNS nerd and have always registered new domains for my projects before I even made the concept of my new ideas. We had tests about the Domain Name System at my professional school and I can&amp;rsquo;t remember I ever not scored the highest&amp;hellip;
So as someone who currently pays for 33 domains a year of which all are for private projects and none generates money I had an idea for a new gTLD which I wanted to operate.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;I am a very big DNS nerd and have always registered new domains for my projects before I even made the concept of my new ideas.
We had tests about the Domain Name System at my professional school and I can&amp;rsquo;t remember I ever not scored the highest&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So as someone who currently pays for 33 domains a year of which all are for private projects and none generates money I had an idea for a new gTLD which I wanted to operate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;New generic top-level domains have a high entry barrier. It&amp;rsquo;s expensive (plan about 200k USD alone for the valuation from the ICANN) and you also have high recurring costs - but is it profitable to operate such a TLD?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first gTLD application round closed in April 2012 and some of the first applicants were already founded years before that.
Some of these new operators are public traded companies and others have to report their balance sheet to governments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Soooo &amp;hellip;. There is data available about those new operators and before I decide if I wanna put such much money on a new TLD I (from an investor perspective) want to know how profitable new gTLDs are.
(As a side note: I am not so rich to operate a new gTLD alone - I would need some support from other investors too ^^)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s why I am writing this post. I need to validate if an investment in a new gTLD is profitable and if the needed energy pays out.
As a modern investor there are tons of other opportunities which pay dividends, interest and more. So if you invest in something specific you should have a good return and reason for that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;registry-operators&#34;&gt;Registry operators&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;donuts&#34;&gt;Donuts&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Donuts Inc is a private domain name registry with 242 new gTLDs. It is the biggest of the new operators by number of TLD endings. The German Wikipedia page about them was initially written by me on the 15 July of 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately I haven&amp;rsquo;t found much financial info about their profit, so they can&amp;rsquo;t simply evaluated by me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;minds--machines&#34;&gt;Minds + Machines&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They are great for a valuation because Minds + Machines Group Limited is a public traded gTLD operator. They weren&amp;rsquo;t profitable for many years, but they were in 2019.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s look at the numbers for the Total comprehensive income / (loss) for the year:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2013: Loss of 222,029 GBP&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2014: Loss of 3,832,128 GBP&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2015: Loss of 677,936 GBP&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2016: Loss of 2,782,107 GBP&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2017: Loss of 84,584 GBP&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2018: Loss of 8,836,970 GBP&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2019: Income of 932,983 GBP&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Minds + Machines also published a June 2020 Interim Report which shows a profit. So I hope the long loss period is over. The share price has decreased in the years because of the bad financials&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have taken the chance to buy some shares because if they turned to profit, then the company is undervalued based on the current share price in my opinion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;dotberlin&#34;&gt;dotBERLIN&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;dotBERLIN GmbH &amp;amp; Co. KG is the German private operator of &amp;ldquo;.berlin&amp;rdquo;. The fine thing about German companies is that they have to report the balance sheets and you can get old balance sheets from the &amp;ldquo;Bundesanzeiger&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The data is not as fresh as from public traded companies, but this analysis is not about fresh data - it&amp;rsquo;s about statistically profitability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A look at the balance sheet doesn&amp;rsquo;t show us an Income statement, but we can see a &amp;ldquo;Shortfall not covered by equity&amp;rdquo; for the years 2019, 2018, 2017, 2016, 2015, 2014, 2013, 2012, 2011, 2010, 2009&amp;hellip; - at that point I just went directly to 2006 and there was also this shortfall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So to me, it looks like dotBERLIN wasn&amp;rsquo;t profitable since founding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is investing in gTLD a good thing for the world? Not really. New gTLD require new servers which need electricity which could be produced environmentally harmful whereas you could invest your money in e.g. new electricity sources like solar or wind parks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many of these providers operated very long without any profit. However some of them (like Minds + Machines) are profitable now and I am invested in Minds + Machines because they are cheap (in my opinion) on the stock exchange, considering they are now profitable and operate with a lovely business model (subscription based service which is essential if you have an online-business)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But you shouldn&amp;rsquo;t take the decision easy if you wanna start a new gTLD registry. As noted - this kind of business seem to take long until it&amp;rsquo;s profitable and other business models like building a new solar park can be better predictable, faster profitable and are better for the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you start a new gTLD, you should expect many years without profit and the need for fresh money from investors. So - it&amp;rsquo;s a bad idea for the most of us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;disclaimer&#34;&gt;Disclaimer&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not investment advice or a buy/sell recommendation. This is my personal opinion and is for information and entertainment purposes only.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everyone acts independently with their financial decision and bears responsibility for it themselves. Trading in securities is always subject to risks and can lead to total loss or debt (e.g. in the case of warrants). Liability is excluded.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
