<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>bash on M5E&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>https://blog.m5e.de/tags/bash/</link>
    <description>Recent content in bash on M5E&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 22 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://blog.m5e.de/tags/bash/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Forget Bash, take Python!</title>
      <link>https://blog.m5e.de/bash/script/python/linux/2020/05/22/forget-bash-take-python.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.m5e.de/bash/script/python/linux/2020/05/22/forget-bash-take-python.html</guid>
      <description>I wrote bash scripts for several years now. You can find old bash scripts of mine on GitHub but most of them aren&amp;rsquo;t maintained anymore - and I have a reason for that.
But before I give you my reasons for not using many bash scripts anymore, lets look at the benefits of bash:
It super easy and you basically already can it if you write Linux / BSD commands There are frameworks out now which give you advanced features like testing It works out of the box on nearly every Linux / BSD system Okay - sounds good - so what&amp;rsquo;s my problem?</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;I wrote bash scripts for several years now. You can find old bash scripts of mine on GitHub but most of them aren&amp;rsquo;t maintained anymore - and I have a reason for that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But before I give you my reasons for not using many bash scripts anymore, lets look at the benefits of bash:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It super easy and you basically already can it if you write Linux / BSD commands&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are frameworks out now which give you advanced features like testing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It works out of the box on nearly every Linux / BSD system&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay - sounds good - so what&amp;rsquo;s my problem?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bash is limited. E.g. it doesn&amp;rsquo;t work out of the box in Windows and I switched my default shell in Linux to fish. But let&amp;rsquo;s break down a few points why Bash isn&amp;rsquo;t optimal for me:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You tend to write platform specific code - e.g. I switched from Debian to Arch Linux and had to replace the &lt;code&gt;apt-get&lt;/code&gt; commands with &lt;code&gt;pacman&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I use fish as default shell. You can use Bash-Scripts with fish, but it&amp;rsquo;s more complicated &amp;hellip;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Linux isn&amp;rsquo;t my only operating system - I run Windows and macOS machines as well.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I love features of higher level programming languages like Python.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And how does Python solve this problem?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It runs out of the box on many Linux systems&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s cross-platform - the same code can run under Linux, Windows, macOS, &amp;hellip; but you also can check the current system and write platform specific code for that&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is also super easy and makes fun&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Testing and more advanced features are build in - no need to install packages&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Like bash, it is already used for automating tasks in many systems (so you can find tons of help online)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can simply access the operating system&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Distribution is also very simple - just create a package and pip can install it from the PyPI, private registry or a Git-Repo&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Languages like Go would also be interesting for automating tasks in your Linux system but Go has things like pointers and types. Python is more similar to Bash - very simple without advanced topics like types or pointers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I created many python scripts for things which solved bash scripts before. And my python scripts all have unit tests and detect the current running operating system. Whereas my bash scripts only worked on Debian systems do my python scripts work on all my used operating systems. So it has saved me a lot of work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I also continue to use little bash scripts for simple tasks like &amp;ldquo;open this on startup&amp;rdquo; - I think it&amp;rsquo;s important to be aware, that higher level languages like python have a big benefit if you want to switch your system but use the same scripts.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Gitea Auto Update Script</title>
      <link>https://blog.m5e.de/gitea/update/upgrade/bash/script/2018/11/26/gitea-auto-update-script.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Nov 2018 21:24:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.m5e.de/gitea/update/upgrade/bash/script/2018/11/26/gitea-auto-update-script.html</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;m a Gitea user for a long time now. Gitea is a nice application to build your own light and fast version of git hosting services like GitHub or GitLab.
Gitea has one problem thought. It doesn&amp;rsquo;t update automatically. A issue for that is open nearly 2 years: https://github.com/go-gitea/gitea/issues/518#issuecomment-441742904
If there is one thing that I really hate, it is that a security sensible web application doesn&amp;rsquo;t update automatically. Because of that I have begun to write a update script for Gitea before 4 months.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m a Gitea user for a long time now. Gitea is a nice application to build your own light and fast version of git hosting services like GitHub or GitLab.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gitea has one problem thought. It doesn&amp;rsquo;t update automatically. A issue for that is open nearly 2 years: &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/go-gitea/gitea/issues/518#issuecomment-441742904&#34;&gt;https://github.com/go-gitea/gitea/issues/518#issuecomment-441742904&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If there is one thing that I really hate, it is that a security sensible web application doesn&amp;rsquo;t update automatically. Because of that I have begun to write a update script for Gitea before 4 months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That script has updated my Gitea instance multiple times now and as I can see, that many users have the same problem (a german blog post from me is my most visited article from outside germany), I want to show you my solution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;warning&#34;&gt;Warning&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned - I am no fan of manual upgrades - because of that I write many auto update scripts for my own systems. This scripts often haven&amp;rsquo;t been tested on other systems and may contain ugly code. 
I am open for the creation of issues or pull requests which optimise my code. You should definitely check the code out and make sure to review it before using it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some creators - e.g. the person behind Kanboard - have a strong option against auto updates. There are good reasons for that too - you may not want to crash your application because of a faulty upgrade. I recommend auto updates only if you create auto backups, too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-script&#34;&gt;The Script&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have published the actual version to GitHub: &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/CMiksche/gitea-auto-update&#34;&gt;https://github.com/CMiksche/gitea-auto-update&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The script was made for a Debian and Arch Linux Systems - I haven&amp;rsquo;t tested it on other systems, but you will definitely encounter errors if you want to use it on Windows, MacOS or a Linux System without systemd (I make bash calls to restart the Gitea service).
You may need to modify the script to work on your system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the Gitea upgrade changes the template files the automatic update may will destroy your custom design because it is a really simple script and doesn&amp;rsquo;t check that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;how-to-use-it&#34;&gt;How to use it&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The usage of my script is easy (please read the paragraphs over this first - it won&amp;rsquo;t work without modifying it if you have no gitea service or no systemd):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Install my script on the system:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;pip install gitea-auto-update&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Create a settings.ini file:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Gitea]
site=https://your-gitea-instance.com/api/v1/version
apiUrl=https://api.github.com/repos/go-gitea/gitea/releases/latest
system=linux-amd64
file=/usr/local/bin/gitea
tmpDir=/tmp/
buildFromSource=
sourceDir=
logFile=update.log
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Change the variables in the settings.ini file&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Enter the command &lt;code&gt;gite-auto-update --settings=/path/to/settings.ini&lt;/code&gt; in your command line to test the first upgrade&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you want to schedule your updates, edit your &lt;code&gt;/etc/crontab&lt;/code&gt; file and add a call to the script&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s it. Please write a issue if my script doesn&amp;rsquo;t works. I am caring if people want to use my script ;-)&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>