<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Group on M5E&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>https://blog.m5e.de/tags/Group/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Group on M5E&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 24 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://blog.m5e.de/tags/Group/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>The Workhorse Group Story</title>
      <link>https://blog.m5e.de/post/the-workhorse-group-story/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.m5e.de/post/the-workhorse-group-story/</guid>
      <description>The Workhorse Group Incorporated is a EV company which primarily produces delivery vans and got lately popular with a rising share price because it was viewed as one of the possible winners of an 8 billion USPS contract to replace old delivery vans.
This contract busted, however I started writing this article before the deal busted - so don&amp;rsquo;t be surprised by the high numbers.
I owned this stock for several years and wanna display my view of the company in this blog post.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;The Workhorse Group Incorporated is a EV company which primarily produces delivery vans and got lately popular with a rising share price because it was viewed as one of the possible winners of an 8 billion USPS contract to replace old delivery vans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This contract busted, however I started writing this article before the deal busted - so don&amp;rsquo;t be surprised by the high numbers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I owned this stock for several years and wanna display my view of the company in this blog post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-usps-deal&#34;&gt;The USPS Deal&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;WKHS has a bad history with the USPS. E.g. a USPS driver was hurt during a prototype test. This isn&amp;rsquo;t the first USPS Deal on which WKHS had bid, more later on&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Competition for WKHS is Oshkosh (with Ford) and Karsan. Oshkosh had also offered a EV solution based on the Ford E-Transit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I thought Oshkosh has a very good chance because they are one of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Top_100_Contractors_of_the_U.S._federal_government&#34;&gt;Top 100 Contractors of the U.S. federal government&lt;/a&gt;. They have lots of experience while Workhorse never had such big contracts and would need help to produce lots of vehicles in a short time (at WKHS they assembled the vehicles via hand in the past, not automated in a factory)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oshkosh won the Deal, however the Valuation of this two stocks before that wasn&amp;rsquo;t on par. WKHS was way higher valuated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-valuation&#34;&gt;The Valuation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Would the Workhorse Group have won an 8 billion contract they probably won&amp;rsquo;t be able to produce all new vehicles in one year. But even if they would do that: Oshkosh had more than 8 billion revenue in 2019 and had a market cap of 6,78 billion USD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Workhorse had at 36,19 USD per stock a market cap of 4,36 billion. So the market cap already was in the area of a company with 8 billion revenue. I don&amp;rsquo;t see any reason why a higher valuation should be justified.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the valuation already had a winning of the contract and a really big EV bonus priced in. It may be fair compared to other EV companies like Tesla, but it definitely isn&amp;rsquo;t fair if you take good old school value figures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-cycle&#34;&gt;The Cycle&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Workhorse Stock is a Story Stock. This is not the first bid for a USPS Deal from Workhorse and you can see when they did bid on a big contract in the stock price history. Most of the times the big deals bust.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Current CEO Duane Hughes has a media background - perfect for marketing a story and if you read a few of the many short reports you see that this is the way with which the management had made money: Market the Story of the big deal and sell shares.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;future&#34;&gt;Future&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dubious YouTube Videos and bad finances should have been a big red flag for every common investor but the EV-Hyped Robinhood Community and Cathie Wood&amp;rsquo;s ARK Invest have pushed this stock without looking too much on the fundamentals and competition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So at the time of the writing the stock crashed after the announcement of the USPS Oshkosh Deal more than 47 percent to 16 USD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can&amp;rsquo;t say for sure if the stock will go up some time in the future again, BUT I am pretty sure if the stock goes up, it will be because some POSSIBLE Deal will get announced again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Make one thing clear: This wasn&amp;rsquo;t a traditional investment, this was a bet on a single Deal which made the most part of the valuation. That&amp;rsquo;s the reason I sold my shares - I don&amp;rsquo;t wanna make bets, I want to own profitable companies which share part of the profit with me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are in the stock market because of Bets, you probably should reconsider your Strategy. Because busted Stories like this can destroy your portfolio.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>