<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>How on M5E&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>https://blog.m5e.de/tags/How/</link>
    <description>Recent content in How on M5E&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 15 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://blog.m5e.de/tags/How/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>How I write my Journal</title>
      <link>https://blog.m5e.de/post/how-i-write-my-journal/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.m5e.de/post/how-i-write-my-journal/</guid>
      <description>Recently I came across a blog post which described some Tips how to write a Journal on Hacker News.
This interested me because I also write a Journal since multiple years (since the 20th March of 2018 to be precise and if we don&amp;rsquo;t count my Journals I had as a child) and it already helped me in multiple occasions.
The author of the article asked himself multiple questions every day and because I think that is too much pressure I want to describe how I do it.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;Recently I came &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=28530120&#34;&gt;across&lt;/a&gt; a blog post which described some Tips how to write a Journal on Hacker News.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This interested me because I also write a Journal since multiple years (since the 20th March of 2018 to be precise and if we don&amp;rsquo;t count my Journals I had as a child) and it already helped me in multiple occasions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The author of the article asked himself multiple questions every day and because I think that is too much pressure I want to describe how I do it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-it-can-be-helpful&#34;&gt;Why it can be helpful&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some possible use cases:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Search when you bought an Item and find out if it still has warranty&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Find out which stock you bought at which price&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When was the trip with your girlfriend again?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How did your business grew so successful?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What did you do back on &amp;hellip;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To summarize: If you keep track of your daily life you can look up everything even if you don&amp;rsquo;t remember something anymore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-i-write-it&#34;&gt;How I write it&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wanted something simple which will last till I die.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a software developer, I use tools like Git for versioning files and Markdown for writing documents (this blog post itself is also written as a Markdown document). Additionally to that, I already had a wiki which was realized as a bunch of Markdown documents and folders in a Git repository hosted on a Raspberry Pi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I used my existing wiki, added a new folder &amp;ldquo;Journal&amp;rdquo; and inside that a folder for the year. That directory contained files named after each month - &amp;ldquo;03.md&amp;rdquo; for example - which had a title for every day and bullet points for every thought.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This simple system exists till this day with a small change that I moved it from my Raspberry Pi to my self-hosted Gitea instance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-personal-finance-is-connected-with-that&#34;&gt;Why personal finance is connected with that&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since this year I use &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/beancount/beancount/&#34;&gt;beancount&lt;/a&gt; to track all my finances in a very similar approach: Files have a special syntax with lines for every transaction and that files get tracked in a Git repository.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks to the parsable syntax you can create reports of your finances (like income and expenses) thus have a better overview of where your money flows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because I trade with stocks since 2014 my journal was heavily used for tracking stock transactions which helped me a lot but obviously such a bookkeeping computer language is a way better solution for that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine you bought a stock but because your Depot was moved to another broker, you don&amp;rsquo;t see the value anymore at which you bought. Now you would have to search old documents of that transaction to find out at which price you can sell to make a profit. In some similar cases this personal tracking of my finances helped me a lot and I would recommend every stock trader writing down the transactions with a system like beancount.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
