<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>stock on M5E&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>https://blog.m5e.de/tags/stock/</link>
    <description>Recent content in stock on M5E&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 12 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://blog.m5e.de/tags/stock/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>SolarWinds Stock Analysis</title>
      <link>https://blog.m5e.de/post/solarwinds-stock-analysis/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.m5e.de/post/solarwinds-stock-analysis/</guid>
      <description>When the SolarWinds supply chain attack happened in 2020, I didn&amp;rsquo;t really get deep into what SolarWinds does because I had to focus on day-to-day business. But now, in 2022, I found out what SolarWinds does because I was searching for monitoring solutions myself.
In this article I want to cover the current valuation, a description of what SolarWinds does and my thoughts about the future.
Valuation As of March 12, the company trades at 11.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;When the SolarWinds supply chain attack happened in 2020, I didn&amp;rsquo;t really get deep into what SolarWinds does because I had to focus on day-to-day business. But now, in 2022, I found out what SolarWinds does because I was searching for monitoring solutions myself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this article I want to cover the current valuation, a description of what SolarWinds does and my thoughts about the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;valuation&#34;&gt;Valuation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As of March 12, the company trades at 11.21 USD per share. That&amp;rsquo;s below book value. The company has an equity ratio of nearly 48% and the revenue for 2021 fell nearly 30% from 2020 and is now at 2017 levels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The companies stock fell nearly 70% in the last few years. So seeing that the book value is higher and the revenue didn&amp;rsquo;t fall as much as the stock price, this seems like an overreaction connected with the hack. But to understand the hack better, let&amp;rsquo;s see what SolarWinds does on a day-to-day basis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;solarwinds-business&#34;&gt;SolarWinds Business&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At it&amp;rsquo;s core, SolarWinds offers IT monitoring solutions. IT professionals may know competitors like PRTG from Paessler AG or Nagios.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These solutions make it easier to control IT infrastructure like Servers, Routers, Switches and more. The goal is to detect a possible problem before an outage happens. So an engineer may get a push notification if e.g. the storage level on a server gets low.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One very big difference to its competitors is that SolarWinds offers a wide range of monitoring solutions. While most competitors focus on special areas - like collecting and analyzing log files or monitoring servers and routers, SolarWinds offers solutions for nearly every area.
SolarWinds archived that by buying smaller companies like e.g. Loggly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A typical customer company has many sensors which collect data and send it to the monitoring dashboard. Because a lot of information can be monitored, these Sensors are in very high numbers (often a company has more sensors than employees)
Think about an international corporation - sensors may be grouped into the different sites around the world and may monitor every single IT device.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If a company wants to switch to another solution from SolarWinds, not only the dashboards, but also every single sensor will most likely need work to be replaced by the new solution. Also, because most competitors only cover some of SolarWinds areas, the switching company will need to make new contracts with multiple new companies.
All-in-all, switching from SolarWinds is hard and expensive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Free, Open Source Solutions exist (I for myself want to use only free software for monitoring my upcoming SaaS company) but again - you have to setup and connect multiple Software Solutions - there is no single one which can easily replace all of SolarWinds features.
For this setup of the Open Source solutions, a lot of time and manpower is required - so it wouldn&amp;rsquo;t surprise me if running SolarWinds is cheaper for big companies than paying all the employees who work on integrating the Open Source Systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-hack&#34;&gt;The Hack&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because SolarWinds monitors so many systems of its customers, this hack has gained so much media attention. To prevent outages, you really have to know a lot of details of your infrastructure, and the attackers could get deep inside this information about SolarWinds customers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the hack was a supply chain attack originated from the build system which SolarWinds uses. This is very interesting to me because I am aware, that many of the world&amp;rsquo;s biggest tech companies have had similar vulnerabilities in the past.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A recent example could be &lt;a href=&#34;https://thehackerblog.com/zero-days-without-incident-compromising-angular-via-expired-npm-publisher-email-domains-7kZplW4x/&#34;&gt;this case&lt;/a&gt;, where a hacker could push malicious code into the Angular framework from Google.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So it&amp;rsquo;s not like this couldn&amp;rsquo;t happen to some of the most well known companies. SolarWinds was probably chosen for the attack because it&amp;rsquo;s monitoring solutions are deeply integrated into the US Government and the biggest American Companies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately for SolarWinds, the hack was a PR disaster. The CEO blamed an intern about an easy password, and that&amp;rsquo;s a no-go from a marketing perspective.
(Because first of all, an intern shouldn&amp;rsquo;t get so much responsibility and second of all, there should be processes to prevent easy to guess passwords)
But to be honest, I don&amp;rsquo;t think that most companies are better than that. This could have happened at nearly every company.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;future&#34;&gt;Future&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SolarWinds customers are deeply integrated into a system which is not easy to replace. So it&amp;rsquo;s hard to know how many of these companies spend the money for switching to a different solution because of this hack.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, such a hack could happen again at a competitor. SolarWinds has a forward P/E of 12.79, the competitor Datadog has a forward P/E of 322.58. That&amp;rsquo;s ridiculous in my eyes, because the same could happen to Datadog and then the revenue could also fall instead of growing high numbers every year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe customers will forget the hack in a few years, but maybe the Image to too damaged and SolarWinds has to rename it&amp;rsquo;s business, spin off all the assets or find another solution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;disclaimer&#34;&gt;Disclaimer&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not investment advice or a buy/sell recommendation. This is my personal opinion and is for information and entertainment purposes only.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everyone acts independently with their financial decision and bears responsibility for it themselves. Trading in securities is always subject to risks and can lead to total loss or debt (e.g. in the case of warrants). Liability is excluded.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Influence of Sanctions on Economies</title>
      <link>https://blog.m5e.de/post/influence-of-sanctions-on-economies/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.m5e.de/post/influence-of-sanctions-on-economies/</guid>
      <description>The current events in Ukraine led to many economic sanctions against Russia. Despite this war is the result of leaders, not their citizens, the West decided to define many very hard sanctions which resulted into making it impossible to trade with Russian Stocks right now. (After the close of the Moscow Exchange, ADRs listed in the US and GDRs listed on the London Stock Exchange also can&amp;rsquo;t be bought anymore)</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;The current &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.m5e.de/post/the-russian-ukrainian-conflict-and-the-stock-market/&#34;&gt;events in Ukraine&lt;/a&gt; led to many economic sanctions against Russia. Despite this war is the result of leaders, not their citizens, the West decided to define many very hard sanctions which resulted into making it impossible to trade with Russian Stocks right now. (After the close of the Moscow Exchange, ADRs listed in the US and GDRs listed on the London Stock Exchange also can&amp;rsquo;t be bought anymore)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because many Russian stocks can only be sold right now, the prices for these fell more and more. Speculators who bought some stocks in the beginning of this Week could get these shares very cheap on the few Exchanges and Brokers which still traded them, but now these Speculators also can&amp;rsquo;t trade Russian stocks anymore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So in this blog post I want to answer the question if these dramatic price deductions are in any relation to the various results of sanctions in recent human history.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;sanctions-against-japan&#34;&gt;Sanctions against Japan&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the second world war was the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ABCD_line&#34;&gt;ABCD line&lt;/a&gt; in which America, Britain, China, and the Dutch stopped selling iron ore, steel and oil to Japan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, Japan found a way of producing 80% of the Oil which was imported by themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;sanctions-against-iran&#34;&gt;Sanctions against Iran&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Iran is the only country which I know of that has faced similar sanctions like Russia currently. A &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.m5e.de/post/alternatives-to-swift/&#34;&gt;SWIFT-Ban&lt;/a&gt; is nothing new to them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kinda similar like Japan, Iran started to produce a lot more of which was imported previously by themselves. This seem to be a good strategy. The Iranian Economy actually grew despite the Sanctions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One important thing to note here is that western investors don&amp;rsquo;t have a easy way to invest in Iranian stocks. So if Russia would face a similar evolvement, then the Russian economy could grow in a few years above the previous levels, but maybe western shareholders will see nothing of this because the Sanctions make it impossible to invest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;statistics&#34;&gt;Statistics&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a good article out there from which I quoted:&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34; data-dnt=&#34;true&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;&amp;quot;Despite their widespread use on the international stage, economic sanctions are largely ineffective in achieving their objectives [...] between 1915 and 2006, comprehensive sanctions were successful, at best, just 30 percent of the time.&amp;quot; &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/O5sUbT6VY3&#34;&gt;https://t.co/O5sUbT6VY3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Christoph Miksche (@CMiksche) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/CMiksche/status/1499665643246919680?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;March 4, 2022&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Statistically and by looking at previous examples we can find out that Capitalism and Economy is stronger than political Sanctions. Most countries can grow economically even when the biggest powers in this world don&amp;rsquo;t like it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, for foreign Investors, Sanctions can make it very hard and destroy their investment. E.g. in Russia only a few percent of the population use Credit cards, so the impact on companies like Visa and Mastercard is probably bigger then the worries of most Russians.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So if you look from a foreign Investors perspective, then the question is not if Russia will grow again (thats very likely), it is if your country or the Exchanges you use allow you to invest in Russia - that&amp;rsquo;s the bigger Issue for you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want to note that I am not trying to defend Russia or any other country mentioned here - in all examples there was a good reason to sanction the mentioned countries but from a rational perspective a sanction will most likely improve the local economy so that it is not so vulnerable from outside influences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;disclaimer&#34;&gt;Disclaimer&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not investment advice or a buy/sell recommendation. This is my personal opinion and is for information and entertainment purposes only.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everyone acts independently with their financial decision and bears responsibility for it themselves. Trading in securities is always subject to risks and can lead to total loss or debt (e.g. in the case of warrants). Liability is excluded.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Russian-Ukrainian War and the Stock Market</title>
      <link>https://blog.m5e.de/post/the-russian-ukrainian-conflict-and-the-stock-market/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.m5e.de/post/the-russian-ukrainian-conflict-and-the-stock-market/</guid>
      <description>In 2008 Russia fought against Georgia in the Russo-Georgian War. This resulted into a catastrophic situation for the people which live in the areas occupied by Russia. Still today, Russia claims that parts of Georgia are &amp;ldquo;independent&amp;rdquo; Countries which do not belong to Georgia.
So why do I start with this story? It&amp;rsquo;s simply because yesterday Putin officially announced to marsh into Ukraine and basically has the same strategy: he says parts of Ukraine are &amp;ldquo;independent&amp;rdquo; Countries which need to be free from Ukraine.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;In 2008 Russia fought against Georgia in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Russo-Georgian_War&#34;&gt;Russo-Georgian War&lt;/a&gt;. This resulted into a catastrophic situation for the people which live in the areas occupied by Russia. Still today, Russia claims that parts of Georgia are &amp;ldquo;independent&amp;rdquo; Countries which do not belong to Georgia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So why do I start with this story? It&amp;rsquo;s simply because yesterday Putin officially announced to marsh into Ukraine and basically has the same strategy: he says parts of Ukraine are &amp;ldquo;independent&amp;rdquo; Countries which need to be free from Ukraine. That is basically the same Strategy Putin uses for years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My primarily interest here is to find out how it will affect the stock market. The best way to make predictions about the future is to look in the past.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back in 2008 the West (EU and US) were concerned but did nothing because they feared a war. If you look completely rational on that, it would mean that you could use drops in the Russian stock market to invest and make a profit in a few years or months&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However: This time it already resulted in consequences: Germany just froze the Nord Stream 2 Project of Gazprom. It is important to note here that Gazprom made big deals with China in recent years - so that could soften the situation of Gazprom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Biden wanted to remove Russia from Visa, Mastercard and SWIFT, but he got criticisms and other important ppl said it wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be that easy to remove Russia from SWIFT, so currently this is just words without consequences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have Stocks around the world and think that if the playbook is similar with the Geogrian Situation, then the Russian stock market will drop a little bit for the next few years and then go back to its normal evolvement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only real big thing which could change that would be if the West really kicks Russia out of SWIFT, fights Russia and maybe even delists Russian stocks (American Depositary Receipts) on the US Exchanges, but that didn&amp;rsquo;t happen in 2008, back then the conflict happened with a Bush Administration.
I am not a U.S. politics expert but if a Republican Politician doesn&amp;rsquo;t start a war in a similar situation, why should a Democratic Politician do that? Aren&amp;rsquo;t they usually the ones which gain votes by saying they are against wars?!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So how should you proceed? If you trade short term, then you can probably get some profit by shortening the Russian stock market. If you invest long term, then you shouldn&amp;rsquo;t think that this will affect Russian companies on the long-term - it didn&amp;rsquo;t in similar situations a few years back so the way international politics work would have to be changed first before it will really have a long-term impact on the Russian stock market.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, you should think about if it is morally acceptable to invest in Russia. That&amp;rsquo;s probably why Russian stocks were so undervalued over the last years: Ppl didn&amp;rsquo;t want to invest in a country ruled by Putin but on the other side ppl who didn&amp;rsquo;t care about moral aspects could make big returns and profit from high dividend yields.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update:&lt;/strong&gt; I found out that Russia already has two alternatives to SWIFT: The SPFS &amp;ldquo;System for Transfer of Financial Messages&amp;rdquo; is basically a SWIFT clone from Russia and the Cross-Border Interbank Payment System (CIPS) is the equivalent from China.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Russia is a Cash focused country, so the ban of MasterCard and VISA would probably hurt these American Companies more than the Russian economy. Quote: &amp;ldquo;Approximately ten percent of payment cards issued in Russia were credit cards&amp;rdquo;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.statista.com/statistics/1099452/credit-card-and-debit-card-number-in-russia/#:~:text=Approximately%20ten%20percent%20of%20payment,250%20million%20of%20these%20cards.&#34;&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;disclaimer&#34;&gt;Disclaimer&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not investment advice or a buy/sell recommendation. This is my personal opinion and is for information and entertainment purposes only.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everyone acts independently with their financial decision and bears responsibility for it themselves. Trading in securities is always subject to risks and can lead to total loss or debt (e.g. in the case of warrants). Liability is excluded.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Evergrande situation</title>
      <link>https://blog.m5e.de/post/the-evergrande-situation/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.m5e.de/post/the-evergrande-situation/</guid>
      <description>Over the last days Evergrande China, the 2nd largest property developer in China after revenue, was in all financial news. More than 1.5 million homes are planned by Evergrande and it has $300 billion in liabilities.
There are fears that Evergrande China will cause another financial crisis like in 2008, comparable to the Lehman Brothers insolvency. I am watching this very carefully. Most of my personal Assets are stocks and a big decline in the stock market could mean damage comparable of loosing multiple yearly incomes to me.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;Over the last days Evergrande China, the 2nd largest property developer in China after revenue, was in all financial news. More than 1.5 million homes are planned by Evergrande and it has $300 billion in liabilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are fears that Evergrande China will cause another financial crisis like in 2008, comparable to the Lehman Brothers insolvency. I am watching this very carefully. Most of my personal Assets are stocks and a big decline in the stock market could mean damage comparable of loosing multiple yearly incomes to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-problem&#34;&gt;The Problem&lt;/h2&gt;

  &lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34; data-dnt=&#34;true&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Seems like that &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/Evergrande?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#Evergrande&lt;/a&gt; problem already affects the financial markets…&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Christoph Miksche (@CMiksche) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/CMiksche/status/1439953316340015104?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;September 20, 2021&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If they company fails to pay the liabilities it could cause a systematic insolvency because the banks wouldn&amp;rsquo;t the get money and the market would be flooded with very cheap homes which could cause insolvency of other property developers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem would affect China first because western banks don&amp;rsquo;t have a big share in the 300 billion - mostly Chinese banks gave the money but if there would be a systematic failure in China the rest of the world would feel that too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most countries have strong trade relationships with China - e.g. the German Car industry sells most of the Cars in China.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s not only real damage, fears of that situation already caused a decline in nearly every stock market index.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-solution-opinion-of-experts&#34;&gt;The Solution (Opinion of Experts)&lt;/h2&gt;

  &lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34; data-dnt=&#34;true&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;As far as I understand it most experts believe the chinese government will support the competition to takeover parts of Evergrande and solve the problem that way without a crisis.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;If that doesn&amp;#39;t happen we could have a Lehman moment.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Christoph Miksche (@CMiksche) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/CMiksche/status/1440249711051427844?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;September 21, 2021&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most Experts think this will be solved like Long-Term Capital Management. To make it short: in the LTCM case, the competition took over parts of the business and the government supported it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-thoughts&#34;&gt;My Thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;

  &lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34; data-dnt=&#34;true&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Over the last months the chinese goverment destroed whole sectors (e.g. E-Learning) without any help - so I wouldn&amp;#39;t bet on support.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Also the company already tried to sell parts without much success and the competiton already has high debts...&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Christoph Miksche (@CMiksche) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/CMiksche/status/1440249732756959241?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;September 21, 2021&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The solution which the Experts share has two assumptions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The government is interested to help solving the issue.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The competition can take over parts from Evergrande&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have very high doubts that this assumptions are correct.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;About 1: In the last months, China created rules which destroyed whole sectors. E.g. they destroyed the whole E-Learning sector. It is basically forbidden to sell E-Learning services. So it doesn&amp;rsquo;t look like the top priority of the government would be supporting financial markets or companies. It looks more like it is more important to them that the government is stronger than companies. Letting financial markets fail could cause a big financial trouble but it actually could be in the favor of the politicians who want a strong government and weak companies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Western &amp;ldquo;Experts&amp;rdquo; make the assumptions China would act like a capitalist nation, but China isn&amp;rsquo;t the US. So we can&amp;rsquo;t expect they make the same decisions as we would make. They have different interests and priorities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;About 2: The competition has also debts. I am not sure if they are strong enough to take over such a big transaction. Remember: more than 1.5 million homes and 300 billion liabilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;disclaimer&#34;&gt;Disclaimer&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not investment advice or a buy/sell recommendation. This is my personal opinion and is for information and entertainment purposes only.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everyone acts independently with their financial decision and bears responsibility for it themselves. Trading in securities is always subject to risks and can lead to total loss or debt (e.g. in the case of warrants). Liability is excluded.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Difference between Wirecard and Steinhoff</title>
      <link>https://blog.m5e.de/post/the-difference-between-wirecard-and-steinhoff/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.m5e.de/post/the-difference-between-wirecard-and-steinhoff/</guid>
      <description>Wirecard and Steinhoff are both companies of German origin which had accounting scandals. In this post I want to describe why these two accounting scandals are completely different and why I choose to take a long position in Steinhoff after the scandal, although I did make a profit with a short position in Wirecard.
I am writing this article because I want to describe that shorting a stock with an accounting scandal / fraud isn&amp;rsquo;t always the best option.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;Wirecard and Steinhoff are both companies of German origin which had accounting scandals. In this post I want to describe why these two accounting scandals are completely different and why I choose to take a long position in Steinhoff after the scandal, although I did make a profit with a short position in Wirecard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am writing this article because I want to describe that shorting a stock with an accounting scandal / fraud isn&amp;rsquo;t always the best option. Sometimes this can be a chance for a long position.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;the-wirecard-scandal&#34;&gt;The Wirecard Scandal&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wirecard is a German payment processor and financial services provider. It was higher valued than any German Bank and viewed as very successful by many German Investors because of a growing revenue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2020 it was reported in an audit that €1.9 billion were &amp;ldquo;missing&amp;rdquo;. I shorted Wirecard after the announcement because it meant that the majority of Wirecards revenue didn&amp;rsquo;t exist while there were multiple billion Euro of credit from banks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I realized that there was a way higher debt to the creditors than actual revenue or profit which could pay for the credit, so there was no real way that Wirecard could save itself from insolvency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, Wirecard is a payments provider used by companies — which company does trust a payment provider which manipulates balance sheets?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;the-steinhoff-scandal&#34;&gt;The Steinhoff Scandal&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Steinhoff International is an international retail holding company. Before the scandal it was the second-biggest furniture company in the World after IKEA.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Basically the scandal which took off in 2017 was that Steinhoff manipulated transactions worth of $7.36 billion from the years 2009 to 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now comes one important part: The revenue alone in 2017 was nearly 19 billion Euro!!! Even if you subtract all manipulated transactions from that there is still value!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Steinhoff also is a holding company which holds many different companies which can be sold. That&amp;rsquo;s what happened after the scandal: Many subsidiaries were sold.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;the-difference&#34;&gt;The Difference&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the financial side:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wirecard made up most of the revenue&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Steinhoff didn&amp;rsquo;t made up most, but part of the revenue&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the strategic side:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wirecard was basically one company which hadn&amp;rsquo;t much to sell&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Steinhoff had many companies with actual real estate and products — many things to sell&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;my-opinion&#34;&gt;My Opinion&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I bought Steinhoff shares after the scandal because I estimated that after selling some of the subsidiaries there would be enough money for paying the creditors and restructuring the company.
That process is still ongoing and Steinhoff still exists. Why? Because they simply had more value and the manipulations were in an area where it was possible to pay them down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I shorted Wirecard because there was noting to hope. With basically all revenue made up there is no real revenue which could help paying the credits down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You should look at the actual numbers after an accounting scandal. I also know there were investigations about an accounting issue at GE, but I didn&amp;rsquo;t see it effecting the share price too much — because the numbers in question were too small.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Putting all accounting scandals into the same bucket is wrong, but I experienced that happens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(To be honest I was laughing my ass off because there are German finance influencers which always talked bad about Investors in Steinhoff but then were heavily invested in Wirecard, didn&amp;rsquo;t see that scandal coming and even invested after there were many signs that the balance sheet was faked)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;disclaimer&#34;&gt;Disclaimer&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not investment advice or a buy/sell recommendation. This is my personal opinion and is for information and entertainment purposes only.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everyone acts independently with their financial decision and bears responsibility for it themselves. Trading in securities is always subject to risks and can lead to total loss or debt (e.g. in the case of warrants). Liability is excluded.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Analyzing the profitability of gTLD registry operators</title>
      <link>https://blog.m5e.de/post/analyzing-the-profitability-of-gtld-registry-operators/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.m5e.de/post/analyzing-the-profitability-of-gtld-registry-operators/</guid>
      <description>I am a very big DNS nerd and have always registered new domains for my projects before I even made the concept of my new ideas. We had tests about the Domain Name System at my professional school and I can&amp;rsquo;t remember I ever not scored the highest&amp;hellip;
So as someone who currently pays for 33 domains a year of which all are for private projects and none generates money I had an idea for a new gTLD which I wanted to operate.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;I am a very big DNS nerd and have always registered new domains for my projects before I even made the concept of my new ideas.
We had tests about the Domain Name System at my professional school and I can&amp;rsquo;t remember I ever not scored the highest&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So as someone who currently pays for 33 domains a year of which all are for private projects and none generates money I had an idea for a new gTLD which I wanted to operate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;New generic top-level domains have a high entry barrier. It&amp;rsquo;s expensive (plan about 200k USD alone for the valuation from the ICANN) and you also have high recurring costs - but is it profitable to operate such a TLD?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first gTLD application round closed in April 2012 and some of the first applicants were already founded years before that.
Some of these new operators are public traded companies and others have to report their balance sheet to governments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Soooo &amp;hellip;. There is data available about those new operators and before I decide if I wanna put such much money on a new TLD I (from an investor perspective) want to know how profitable new gTLDs are.
(As a side note: I am not so rich to operate a new gTLD alone - I would need some support from other investors too ^^)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s why I am writing this post. I need to validate if an investment in a new gTLD is profitable and if the needed energy pays out.
As a modern investor there are tons of other opportunities which pay dividends, interest and more. So if you invest in something specific you should have a good return and reason for that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;registry-operators&#34;&gt;Registry operators&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;donuts&#34;&gt;Donuts&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Donuts Inc is a private domain name registry with 242 new gTLDs. It is the biggest of the new operators by number of TLD endings. The German Wikipedia page about them was initially written by me on the 15 July of 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately I haven&amp;rsquo;t found much financial info about their profit, so they can&amp;rsquo;t simply evaluated by me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;minds--machines&#34;&gt;Minds + Machines&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They are great for a valuation because Minds + Machines Group Limited is a public traded gTLD operator. They weren&amp;rsquo;t profitable for many years, but they were in 2019.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s look at the numbers for the Total comprehensive income / (loss) for the year:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2013: Loss of 222,029 GBP&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2014: Loss of 3,832,128 GBP&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2015: Loss of 677,936 GBP&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2016: Loss of 2,782,107 GBP&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2017: Loss of 84,584 GBP&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2018: Loss of 8,836,970 GBP&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2019: Income of 932,983 GBP&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Minds + Machines also published a June 2020 Interim Report which shows a profit. So I hope the long loss period is over. The share price has decreased in the years because of the bad financials&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have taken the chance to buy some shares because if they turned to profit, then the company is undervalued based on the current share price in my opinion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;dotberlin&#34;&gt;dotBERLIN&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;dotBERLIN GmbH &amp;amp; Co. KG is the German private operator of &amp;ldquo;.berlin&amp;rdquo;. The fine thing about German companies is that they have to report the balance sheets and you can get old balance sheets from the &amp;ldquo;Bundesanzeiger&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The data is not as fresh as from public traded companies, but this analysis is not about fresh data - it&amp;rsquo;s about statistically profitability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A look at the balance sheet doesn&amp;rsquo;t show us an Income statement, but we can see a &amp;ldquo;Shortfall not covered by equity&amp;rdquo; for the years 2019, 2018, 2017, 2016, 2015, 2014, 2013, 2012, 2011, 2010, 2009&amp;hellip; - at that point I just went directly to 2006 and there was also this shortfall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So to me, it looks like dotBERLIN wasn&amp;rsquo;t profitable since founding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is investing in gTLD a good thing for the world? Not really. New gTLD require new servers which need electricity which could be produced environmentally harmful whereas you could invest your money in e.g. new electricity sources like solar or wind parks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many of these providers operated very long without any profit. However some of them (like Minds + Machines) are profitable now and I am invested in Minds + Machines because they are cheap (in my opinion) on the stock exchange, considering they are now profitable and operate with a lovely business model (subscription based service which is essential if you have an online-business)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But you shouldn&amp;rsquo;t take the decision easy if you wanna start a new gTLD registry. As noted - this kind of business seem to take long until it&amp;rsquo;s profitable and other business models like building a new solar park can be better predictable, faster profitable and are better for the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you start a new gTLD, you should expect many years without profit and the need for fresh money from investors. So - it&amp;rsquo;s a bad idea for the most of us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;disclaimer&#34;&gt;Disclaimer&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not investment advice or a buy/sell recommendation. This is my personal opinion and is for information and entertainment purposes only.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everyone acts independently with their financial decision and bears responsibility for it themselves. Trading in securities is always subject to risks and can lead to total loss or debt (e.g. in the case of warrants). Liability is excluded.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Workhorse Group Story</title>
      <link>https://blog.m5e.de/post/the-workhorse-group-story/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.m5e.de/post/the-workhorse-group-story/</guid>
      <description>The Workhorse Group Incorporated is a EV company which primarily produces delivery vans and got lately popular with a rising share price because it was viewed as one of the possible winners of an 8 billion USPS contract to replace old delivery vans.
This contract busted, however I started writing this article before the deal busted - so don&amp;rsquo;t be surprised by the high numbers.
I owned this stock for several years and wanna display my view of the company in this blog post.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;The Workhorse Group Incorporated is a EV company which primarily produces delivery vans and got lately popular with a rising share price because it was viewed as one of the possible winners of an 8 billion USPS contract to replace old delivery vans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This contract busted, however I started writing this article before the deal busted - so don&amp;rsquo;t be surprised by the high numbers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I owned this stock for several years and wanna display my view of the company in this blog post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-usps-deal&#34;&gt;The USPS Deal&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;WKHS has a bad history with the USPS. E.g. a USPS driver was hurt during a prototype test. This isn&amp;rsquo;t the first USPS Deal on which WKHS had bid, more later on&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Competition for WKHS is Oshkosh (with Ford) and Karsan. Oshkosh had also offered a EV solution based on the Ford E-Transit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I thought Oshkosh has a very good chance because they are one of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Top_100_Contractors_of_the_U.S._federal_government&#34;&gt;Top 100 Contractors of the U.S. federal government&lt;/a&gt;. They have lots of experience while Workhorse never had such big contracts and would need help to produce lots of vehicles in a short time (at WKHS they assembled the vehicles via hand in the past, not automated in a factory)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oshkosh won the Deal, however the Valuation of this two stocks before that wasn&amp;rsquo;t on par. WKHS was way higher valuated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-valuation&#34;&gt;The Valuation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Would the Workhorse Group have won an 8 billion contract they probably won&amp;rsquo;t be able to produce all new vehicles in one year. But even if they would do that: Oshkosh had more than 8 billion revenue in 2019 and had a market cap of 6,78 billion USD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Workhorse had at 36,19 USD per stock a market cap of 4,36 billion. So the market cap already was in the area of a company with 8 billion revenue. I don&amp;rsquo;t see any reason why a higher valuation should be justified.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the valuation already had a winning of the contract and a really big EV bonus priced in. It may be fair compared to other EV companies like Tesla, but it definitely isn&amp;rsquo;t fair if you take good old school value figures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-cycle&#34;&gt;The Cycle&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Workhorse Stock is a Story Stock. This is not the first bid for a USPS Deal from Workhorse and you can see when they did bid on a big contract in the stock price history. Most of the times the big deals bust.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Current CEO Duane Hughes has a media background - perfect for marketing a story and if you read a few of the many short reports you see that this is the way with which the management had made money: Market the Story of the big deal and sell shares.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;future&#34;&gt;Future&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dubious YouTube Videos and bad finances should have been a big red flag for every common investor but the EV-Hyped Robinhood Community and Cathie Wood&amp;rsquo;s ARK Invest have pushed this stock without looking too much on the fundamentals and competition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So at the time of the writing the stock crashed after the announcement of the USPS Oshkosh Deal more than 47 percent to 16 USD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can&amp;rsquo;t say for sure if the stock will go up some time in the future again, BUT I am pretty sure if the stock goes up, it will be because some POSSIBLE Deal will get announced again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Make one thing clear: This wasn&amp;rsquo;t a traditional investment, this was a bet on a single Deal which made the most part of the valuation. That&amp;rsquo;s the reason I sold my shares - I don&amp;rsquo;t wanna make bets, I want to own profitable companies which share part of the profit with me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are in the stock market because of Bets, you probably should reconsider your Strategy. Because busted Stories like this can destroy your portfolio.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;disclaimer&#34;&gt;Disclaimer&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not investment advice or a buy/sell recommendation. This is my personal opinion and is for information and entertainment purposes only.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everyone acts independently with their financial decision and bears responsibility for it themselves. Trading in securities is always subject to risks and can lead to total loss or debt (e.g. in the case of warrants). Liability is excluded.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why Bumble is overvalued</title>
      <link>https://blog.m5e.de/post/why-bumble-is-overvalued/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.m5e.de/post/why-bumble-is-overvalued/</guid>
      <description>Yesterday Bumble had it&amp;rsquo;s initial public offering (IPO). The starting price was 43 USD, a valuation of more than 8 billion and it shot up to 76 USD, a valuation of over 13 billion.
Despite this high valuation, the company lastly made a net loss and only a few hundred million ($376.6 million) in revenue.
The Risk The current market for Tech, EV and Cannabis stocks is in a hype bubble.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;Yesterday Bumble had it&amp;rsquo;s initial public offering (IPO). The starting price was 43 USD, a valuation of more than 8 billion and it shot up to 76 USD, a valuation of over 13 billion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite this high valuation, the company lastly made a net loss and only a few hundred million ($376.6 million) in revenue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-risk&#34;&gt;The Risk&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The current market for Tech, EV and Cannabis stocks is in a hype bubble. I made profit with some overvalued stocks and currently sell these and rebalance my portfolio with more value stocks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But this is not the only risk. I&amp;rsquo;ve used Dating Apps since multiple months (I also made a &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.m5e.de/post/fighting-tinderplusplus-malware/&#34;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt; about a problem with Tinder) and I think the market will evolve:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;enter-the-world-of-facebook&#34;&gt;Enter the World of Facebook&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Facebook launched its own Dating service: Facebook Dating&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think this will dominate the market in a few years - why?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nearly all popular Dating Apps use Facebook Data / Login for registration and validation of the user
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Facebook already has data like Profile Photos, Workplace, Interests,&amp;hellip; which are important in the wold of online dating&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Facebook already has methods to validate profiles&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Facebook already has a bigger user base than all of the dating competition
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To me it seems like the user base of Facebook Dating is already bigger than the user base of Bumble in my local area&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve encountered no limits in swipes or other things
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All features which are premium on the competition Apps are free on Facebook&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve encountered no Ads in Facebook Dating&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I guess this depends on the individual, but I&amp;rsquo;ve got more matches in a few days on Facebook Dating than in multiple months on Bumble&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Facebook promotes social connections - you see who is Friends with other Facebook Friends of you on Facebook
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This adds validation - you trust the other side more that it is not a fake profile&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why should users register with Facebook on Third-Party-Apps if Facebook already provides a superior Dating experience?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Currently many people don&amp;rsquo;t know about Facebook Dating, but Facebook is a Advertising Platform with a giant user base - so it should be very easy to gain more and more people until the competition dies out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It looks like the Investors in Bumble aren&amp;rsquo;t aware that this big competitor is out there and the IPO money was needed for Bumble to have a chance fighting them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;disclaimer&#34;&gt;Disclaimer&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not investment advice or a buy/sell recommendation. This is my personal opinion and is for information and entertainment purposes only.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everyone acts independently with their financial decision and bears responsibility for it themselves. Trading in securities is always subject to risks and can lead to total loss or debt (e.g. in the case of warrants). Liability is excluded.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On the 23andMe and VGAC Merger</title>
      <link>https://blog.m5e.de/post/on-the-23andme-and-vgac-merger/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.m5e.de/post/on-the-23andme-and-vgac-merger/</guid>
      <description>On the 4th February 2021 23andMe and VG Acquisition Corp announced that they will merge, bringing 23andMe into the public.
As VGAC is already tradable in the public market, the shares have skyrocketed to 19 USD. But this is crazy&amp;hellip;
Why this is crazy? First you should know that the initiators of a SPAC commonly have additional rights to e.g. buy additional shares. They also mostly pay 10 USD per share.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;On the 4th February 2021 23andMe and VG Acquisition Corp announced that they will merge, bringing 23andMe into the public.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As VGAC is already tradable in the public market, the shares have skyrocketed to 19 USD. But this is crazy&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-this-is-crazy&#34;&gt;Why this is crazy?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First you should know that the initiators of a SPAC commonly have additional rights to e.g. buy additional shares. They also mostly pay 10 USD per share. I don&amp;rsquo;t go more into detail here, but I want to talk about the shareholders which buy VGAC at the current 19 USD price WITHOUT additional rights like the initiators.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you look at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://vgacquisition.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/02/23andMe-Investor-Presentation.pdf&#34;&gt;Investor Presentation&lt;/a&gt; these VGAC shareholders will only get 11 % of the combined company! BUT the market cap of VGAC at 19.05 USD is 876.30 Mn!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So if you buy VGAC at 19 USD you don&amp;rsquo;t get 23andMe at a $3.5 billion valuation like Vigrin and the other investors - Nooo, you buy at a way higher price. 19 USD per VGAC share, 11 % of VGAC go into 23andMe would result into a nearly 8 billion valuation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To put it into comparison: At 19 USD per share you nearly buy at a valuation (8 billion) at which the institutional investors bought Ancestry ($4.7 billion) and 23andMe ($3.5 billion) combined.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also: 23andMe had declining revenue in the past years and does only make around 200 million revenue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You buy a business at a valuation at 8 billion which makes only around 200 million revenue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to buy 23andMe you should wait till the merger is done because the current VGAC market cap is way too high considering existing VGAC shareholders will only get a little part of the combined company.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A alternative investment Idea could be OraSure Technologies Inc - these are the producers of the diagnostic testing kits which are used by 23andMe and Ancestry. Current market cap only 989,83 Mio USD, the sales have declined from 181,74 Mio in 2018 to 154,60 Mio in 2019 but looks like a fair or even cheap valuation to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;disclaimer&#34;&gt;Disclaimer&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not investment advice or a buy/sell recommendation. This is my personal opinion and is for information and entertainment purposes only.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everyone acts independently with their financial decision and bears responsibility for it themselves. Trading in securities is always subject to risks and can lead to total loss or debt (e.g. in the case of warrants). Liability is excluded.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
